Tariq Islam: With an interest
first, right? Yes.
Jamie Duncan: Thanks for joining
us joining us today on episode
10 of the K files. My name is
Jamie Duncan. I'm a customer
engineer at Google, with me as
always, is john Osborne. I run
this as john Osborne, chief
architect for Red Hat, public
sector. And tark Islam.
Everyone, this is Tarik Islam,
sales engineering manager at
Google. Um, we've been having a
discussion for about 10 minutes.
Now before we click the Record
button. We know what we want to
talk about, but we're not 100%
sure what to call it.
We've called it get ops and it's
not quite get Ops, we've called
it ci CD. And it's not quite
that. JOHN, you said the CN CF
has a name on application
development and delivery,
something like that.
John Osborne: Yeah, so Helm is a
is a CNC f project that
graduated this year. And they
have it filed under application
definition. And deployment, I
think, okay,
Jamie Duncan: but that's your
target quote was immediately
hated it. Yes. Like
Tariq Islam: that right under
thanks. I hated
John Osborne: definition and
development. That's what they
have it. Mission development,
probably
Jamie Duncan: the most accurate
definition tark throughout was
called up CD. So Ops, continuous
delivery. Really, what we're
going to spend about we're gonna
spend a little time talking
about is how you once your
cluster is deployed, but not
doing the actual development of
the application. What happens in
the middle, what tools are there
out there to configure your
cluster to set up all those
security setup all the policies
to set up all the configurations
and the bits and the bytes, and
get your cluster ready for
applications and then deploy and
manage those application life
cycles?
Tariq Islam: So it's
interesting, you mentioned it
that way, Jamie? Because it just
kind of occurred to me that this
is actually how we see a lot of
organizations adopt things
across the timeline. They Oh, it
always starts with Okay, I'm
gonna get my cluster stood up.
But then how do I actually like
manage this thing, day to ops is
maybe synonymous with this
topic, a little bit, right?
cluster configuration,
environment configuration, what
does all that look like? And
then they start worrying about
creating a harness for for
application delivery.
John Osborne: And and maybe that
that'll be the segue for us and
to see ICD? It's been probably,
to me, like the most fragmented
space, right? I mean, we're like
six years into Kubernetes. And
there's been a ton of these
projects that have just kind of
been hot for like a year, and
then he never really heard it
from them again, right?
Jamie Duncan: I mean, he was
what, two and a half years ago,
we we went over to tartes office
in Northern Virginia, and looked
at what case on it and
John Osborne: chase on it.
Jamie Duncan: json at ham
sandwich sauna. I mean, there
were a ton of them that we
looked at, and I haven't heard
of most of them. Since that day,
when we stole free lunch from
Google.
Tariq Islam: I actually forgot
it existed.
Unknown: Exactly.
Tariq Islam: Wow, man, it's been
a while. I mean, this ecosystem
is full like it's kind of
defined as in the beginning
there was Helm in Helm was
pretty okay. Well, it fill the
gap. It I mean, it it filled it
filled a, an implicit need for
any sis ops team, any sis ops
team worth, it's worth its
weight, right? If I'm gonna
adopt Kubernetes, I really I
need to be able to define define
the gates, I need to define the
guardrails and Helm did does a
great job at that, of that, at
least at some scale, but perhaps
not at scale. And maybe we can
talk about that today. But it
definitely filled a need. I
forgot how wild Kubernetes was
in the early days until I went
back to this episode and started
looking at Helm to and like all
this stuff came back like what
Helm was first released, there
was no our back in Kubernetes at
all, and like and then how
maintains like, this whole
state, in its its own outside of
Kubernetes, because there was no
CR DS or anything like that.
And, and everything used to run
his route. And, you know, all
the Docker images would mount to
the home and the battles that
were fought. Yeah, you know, so.
So let's do this. Let's, let's,
uh, let's define Helm real
quick. For the folks listening,
just, you know, for good podcast
hygiene here. I'll take, I'll
take a crack at it, it's
probably gonna be half half
wrong. What's gonna be half
right?
It'll be half right. I've always
seen Helm as as, as a
templating. approach to to. I
almost have to say Git ops.
Again, I don't want to overload
that term.
John Osborne: package
management, maybe?
Tariq Islam: Yes, exactly. It's
application package, not
application pack. Because
remember treating your
applications in a packaged way.
But it's, it's it's a, it's a
templating. It's a templating
tool effectively. I mean, it's
almost like a DSL. And it's very
specific. And it is important to
note by the way that that Helm
is. It's It's different from
customize. I'm introducing that
term early on, because as soon
as you Google Helm or customize,
in your, in the Google quick
results, you actually see, like
one of the first results is Helm
versus customize. So we'll talk
about customize as well. But
there seems to be a bit of a not
a battle going on. But folks are
wondering which one to use when
and why hounding the first one
to Market. But templating is how
I would have I would describe
it,
John Osborne: that's how I think
of it as I mean, to me, like my
mental map, our model is I still
kind of think of it like Jinja
templates in Python, but that's
probably shortchanging some of
some of this. Yep. Similar
capabilities. But
Jamie Duncan: it really it feels
a lot like To me it feels like
Ansible for Kubernetes.
Tariq Islam: Is it though, I'm
channeling my, my Thor right
now.
Jamie Duncan: That's what. And
as I was saying that I five
seconds previously, because I,
you know, in my brain out my
mouth, I wonder if I feel that
way, because that's when I
really learned both of those
tools. I learned them sort of
beside one another. Or if
there's a relationships there, I
think there's at least some
relationships there. Because
john, you know, explicitly
called out Jinja templates,
which is how you do templates in
Ansible.
Unknown: Mm hmm.
Jamie Duncan: there on the
surface, there are at least some
similarities. But what Ansible
is, at the end of the day is
largely a templating engine. So
they have
Tariq Islam: maybe a right that
actually, if you're going by
that description, because that's
how I mean, that's how that's
how we see helm. Now. I mean,
that being said, though, I think
there's there's a discussion
happening right now around
whether whether a, an ops team
that's managing this Kubernetes
platform should use Helm or
customize is the room to use
both. Maybe I'll nip that last
one in the bud right now and say
using both is just going to add
way too much complexity. But I
think it's a good discussion.
Because if you if you look at
the the structure of helm, I
mean, it's come a long way in
terms of its architecture as
well. They look at security
concerns, initially, you had
client side, server side
components, and now you don't,
they've done a great job of
locking certain things down and
addressing the security concerns
that were
John Osborne: that were there
early on. If you were in the in
the early days, you know, they
have these in the old version of
Helm a this thing called tiller,
which basically, yeah, it's
mashed up all the template was
basically was the templating
engine and would just apply
everything to the Kubernetes
API, there was no security
because it didn't exist in
Kubernetes. But do you actually
remember the beginning? And I
forgot about this until I
started going back and look at
some wild stuff, but it would
actually just deploy everything
in the coop system namespace.
Jamie Duncan: That's all it
would do.
John Osborne: Well, that was
like the default namespace it
would deploy to. So yeah, so he
was not iterating. And all of a
sudden, you're just not really,
yeah. Which is a really good way
to like FUBAR your cluster, but
I do like I do like helm. It did
fill a gap in the beginning. But
if you also look at a lot of the
tools that have been around,
it's the only one, like,
customize as much as someone new
right, like out of the first
generation of tools. It's the
only way to hell yeah, still
here.
Tariq Islam: So john, and your
and so if I were to ask you the
question, I don't think we've
addressed this for for the, for
the folks listening, what what
do I use Helm for?
John Osborne: I always, so two
parts that I always felt like,
especially in the early days of
Kubernetes, but still probably
to this day, one of the big
things about it was actually the
content around it. So there's
like a Helm chart that exists
for almost anything. So if you
want to go install MySQL on
Kubernetes, or, or,
you know, some Apache project
or, or WordPress, because every
example is WordPress, right? You
can just go you can just type
Helm install, and it'll pull in
a chart that has that for you.
Now, there's of course, like,
you know, there's security
concerns around that. There's,
there's ways to do that more
securely, but to get up and
running the content around it,
almost like Docker, right? Like
if you think about when Docker
was really big. In the
beginning, it was more. There's
all these based, yes, they did
everything with API, all that
stuff. But I think a big reason
was they have the ecosystem,
right, and Cal has the
ecosystem. But I don't think it
works that well for individual
use cases. But it does work well
for teams that are going to
gate. At least that's where I
start. See it. And that's where
I see people using it as more
like, you know, ops teams or
some, some team that's going to
gate resources to a developer,
but they're going to give them
access to certain variables,
then you can, they can give them
Helm charts that they can
override certain things, but not
certain other things. I also see
kind of, sometimes in the
enterprise teams will have like,
they'll allow, say, like five
variations on let's use like
Tomcat as a simple example. But
they're going to allow you five,
five variations of Tomcat rate
and Helm is a kind of a good way
to lock down Tomcat, but just
give you the five variations,
and you can kind of pick and
choose with the templating.
Tariq Islam: Yeah, and so
that's, that's where I feel like
Helm starts to come apart a bit,
because of all the possible
variations that you start
running into as an organization.
You know, if I've got five
variations, you know, in a
couple years, I might end up
becoming 15 different
variations. And I think that's
where the discussion with
between Helm and customize comes
into play. Do I want to do like
templating till till I die? Or
do I want to actually start
leveraging an overlay based
system? Like the one customize
represents? I mean, we haven't
we haven't even defined
customize. Yep. But I think
that's that's the question.
John Osborne: Do you want to
define customers?
Tariq Islam: Yeah, so so
customize. It's not it's not
templating? It's primarily it's,
it isn't work, for lack of a
better term, an overlay engine,
right. And the unique thing
about customize is that it's
actually baked into the cube
CTL. See, ally. So you can use
the dash k flag to use it. from
an engineering standpoint, it's
it's maintained by, you know,
core Kubernetes, whereas Helm
is, is maintained by by a third
party, said, distributors, what
John Osborne: is the third? I
mean, it seems mostly IBM and
Microsoft, from what I've seen,
but
Tariq Islam: yeah, that's what
I've seen as well. That's what I
mean by third party. I'm not
saying that it's outside the
community. But the fact that
customize is part of you know,
the coop CTL. See, Li like the
that actual flow, just kind of
intrinsically brings it closer
to the Kubernetes platform. And
I'm, I've always been a bit of a
purist slash, minimalist slash,
whatever, just, I like that type
of thing, right? Just bring me
up, keep me as close to
Kubernetes as you as you
possibly can. And I'm happy.
John Osborne: Tell me if my
mental map is just horrible, but
in my mind, I kind of think of
customizes. Like, if I was
working locally, and sort of
scripting things out with sed
and a bunch of other Linux
command line tools, eventually,
when I that mature it, I get
something like customize.
Tariq Islam: That's about right,
man.
Jamie Duncan: Yeah, that's,
yeah, you're certainly in the
right neighborhood, if not at
the right front door. It can
turn on
John Osborne: their eyes.
Jamie Duncan: Right, like Tarik
said there, you can overlay. So
you can you have a directory
called base. And inside base are
all of the objects that you want
to have created when you run
this customize script. So if you
want to create a namespace,
deployment objects, Ingress
objects, whatever, and you can
parameterize those. So in that
regard, it's not drastically
different than helm. And they
even look a little alike. So you
have this base directory, and
then everything you run, pull
starts at that base directory.
But then you can overlay
different things on top of that.
So you can also have a directory
called production or a directory
called development. And you can
populate those parameters with
directory with dev values, or
prod values or your own custom
values. And then you can also
have parameters files, where
you're just filling things in,
or where you override a specific
thing. It gets to the same
place, my biggest, the reason I
use customize more than I use
Helm is that I keep everything
in the repository. The biggest
problem I have with Helm is that
I have to pull in, I have to do
Helm repo add, and then go add
the repository for WordPress
that contains the helm charts,
or for whatever I'm installing.
And then I have to turn around
and tell it to go update those
like, like a package manager,
like using Yum, or apt. And then
they're stored off in some
library folder. And they're not
a part of my repository, where
is customize inside the
Customize library itself. It
just understands what a
namespace, what that yamo looks
like. It understands all these
different things. And I can do
other cool things like for
secrets, I can actually just
have it I can feed it two or
three pieces of information and
have it generate a secret for
me. You do a lot of really cool
little shortcut, things like
that inside customize. And it's
all inside my repo. I don't have
to pull another another chunk of
code down and put like, like
subscribing to a repository.
Tariq Islam: And I think that's
part of the power right for an
organization to be able to start
adopting a thing like, like get
ups, right? I mean, if you're
keeping everything in
repository, it kind of lends
itself towards that. So
immediately, I think it becomes
a lot more scalable. Now, for
me, I still am a fan of helm.
Because it I mean, if you've
installed this do in the last
year, you probably use the helm
install or the helm chart for
it. I love that right? I love
being able to just go to Helm
chart and install something,
it's pre configured pre package
ready to rock. That's been
great. But But to your point,
Jamie, it's I lean more towards
towards customize for for things
that I want to break apart and
put back together for my own
purposes,
John Osborne: it does seem like
in terms of ci CD usage, that I
see more customized now, in
terms of, you know, someone's
going to write some code or it's
going to iterate I know in the
Git ops model, like the default
projects like Argo and flux,
like most of their examples, use
customized as well. I still see
how I'm filling a need. In terms
of the the teams and the people
in that handoff, do you see
customize being used for those
cases as well? or?
Unknown: Yeah,
Jamie Duncan: Yeah, I do. And
because of that overlay idea
that I can, I have a folder that
contains all of the uniqueness
that represents my production
environment. And it's just
labeled production, or a dev a
dev environment or, and I can
split it and slice it and dice
it however I want. And it's
going to take those objects in,
in my base folder, my base
directory, and it's going to add
or subtract from them, as per
the instructions in those in the
customized folders. So I can, I
can get to that same place. And
I can do all of the things that
you're supposed to do inside
there. And it's all and kind of
interesting, when you're talking
about where it's the default for
ci CD. And I think it's just
because it's easier is because
it's part of coop CTL when I
install coop CTL I install
customize all of your container
images that do all of those
builds have coop CTL in them
because they have to, as so and
so I just get all of that
functionality out of the box.
Whereas if I'm using helm, every
time I run that build my
container image has to grab the
repo and pull the repo down and
do all of the things you have to
do to make him work. And that's
time consuming at scale when I'm
doing lots of build today.
John Osborne: So how am I think
one of the reasons why Helm is
so popular just has this massive
ecosystem of existing charts,
right? I mean, is there ways to
plug those charts in to
customize or kind of leverage
that ecosystem? Or or do you
have to use Helm if you want to
leverage all that?
Tariq Islam: You'd have to you'd
have to pull apart the the helm
chart a little bit. Because it's
in its its its own non k
standard format. It's still
YAML. But it's still its own.
That's what I call it. That's
why I mentioned it kind of being
its own DSL earlier. Because you
really it if you're on Helm
today, you've been on Helm for
years and you want to go over to
customize, it's going to be a
migration. That's what you're
effectively looking at. Right?
It's some form of a migration.
John Osborne: I do like how I
customize, it doesn't change the
original YAML that you had.
Makes it Yeah, just makes it
easier. What about in
production? Right? Like, is it?
Do you think there's benefits to
one versus the other? if, you
know, some say some YAML goes
astray, right? Like, what's the
Is there a way you can tell
inside the annotations or inside
the metadata? How that yamo was
constructed in the first place?
Tariq Islam: I don't think that
there's any auditing, how do you
unpack that? I know and
Jamie Duncan: I know, customize
has like a dry run option. In
fact, the default, yeah, just
output YAML. So the way you
actually use customize, you
know, the customized command
reads a dot customize file that
then you tell it you feed it
those parameters, but by
default, it just spits out YAML
and then you actually pipe that
into if you're not using coop
CTL dash k. a bad habit that I
formed early on and still do is
to run the customized command
and then pipe that into coop
CTL.
Tariq Islam: You don't even do
the dry run, you just fly by the
seat.
Jamie Duncan: Exactly like you
get pipe
John Osborne: live production,
Unknown: exact reference or for
the week.
Jamie Duncan: Dry runs for
people with SLA.
John Osborne: Well, yeah, and
Kubernetes does have some of
that built in with the the last
apply configuration annotation
that's in there. Now if you look
in I think it's 118. They added
that where you can go see what
the previous yamo was before it
got applied.
Jamie Duncan: I don't know
there's any way The first time I
saw it.
John Osborne: I don't care for I
don't care for it. I saw in the
Git repo that they people
complained and they said that
people like it because it
provides info but I just feel
like it takes so much space.
That to diverge too much, but
Tariq Islam: religious c li best
practices.
John Osborne: Yeah. But I didn't
know if there's any way to I'm
not it. I'm not expert enough in
either of them even though I've
used both them a decent amount,
but to actually unpack the how
they were created. So you could
see where things went awry.
Jamie Duncan: Yeah, I don't
think there is like it unless
you tell it to. So I have
significantly like, I'm very
much a pure consumer of helm,
where I do exactly what you
said, john, I, you know, I'm
reading the instructions on how
to deploy something that I
haven't deployed before. And it
says, Go grab the helm chart and
run Helm and set these set these
variables. I do exactly. That's,
that's pretty much my experience
with helm. Customize, I've gone
a fair bit deeper, I'm certainly
not an expert by any stretch,
but have, you know, sort of
written some customized schemas
and done some work to deploy to
different environments. So I can
say pretty confidently, like, in
customized, there's not an
inbuilt function to let you do
that. But if, but that idea of
everything's a parameter,
anything I want is a parameter.
I could add, you know,
annotations and labels and all
the things that I would want to
add. to to see any of that
information. I don't know that I
like the idea of debugging that
way. But that's kind of Yeah, I
know what you're getting to
maybe,
John Osborne: yeah, just you
know, any other information, you
know, it's, uh, I'm always, I'm
always looking for how I can
unpack things, you know, how
things gotten to the state, they
got into any any information,
there's good.
Tariq Islam: So Helm was great
initially, because it filled
that gap, right, it filled that
need for, you know, establishing
those guardrails, but I also
felt like it violated, you know,
certain principles around DevOps
and actually brought, it brought
certain things too far over to
the right, I guess. So, you
know, I, I interacted with
organizations that had adopted
Helm and suddenly had developers
using Helm charts and kind of
overreaching into the
infrastructure deployment
process, application deployment
process, and it muddied the
waters quite a bit. And it, it
actually prevented operations
teams from being able to make
certain decisions without, you
know, significantly impacting
everybody else around them,
which is kind of the antithesis
of why they were trying to do
all of this to begin with. And I
found that that customized
somewhat addresses that because
it's not customized is just not
something that a developer
really can worry about, I guess,
given where customize lives, in
the process of creating these
overlays and applying them at a
given moment in time,
Jamie Duncan: right, they could
do it in on their laptop, they
could you know, the, the
customized files are in the
repository. But they couldn't do
it in an environment that
mattered because our back
because of all that stuff that
didn't exist back in the day, to
take care of it. Customize is
able to take advantage of it, I
think, as I look at and we kind
of dogged, not dogged him, but
we certainly, at least I gave it
a poor connotation when we were
talking about all the service
meshes and how hashey corpse
console deploys with the helm
chart. And I said it felt kind
of like 2005
Tariq Islam: I remember that.
Jamie Duncan: Like that is like
that's with a slightly more
intelligent thought on it. I
hope customize is taking the
lessons learned from helm. And
building. prob, for the reasons
you just said tarak, as well as
the the stuff I was talking
about, like where it's, it's
easier for it to live in a
repository without any external
dependencies. It's taking the
lessons learned from Helm and
making it a more cloud native
DevOps friendly get ops
friendly, buzzword friendly
tool.
Tariq Islam: Yeah, I just think
and this is not to say that Helm
had poor design principles that
they certainly don't, they never
did, but I think they fell
victim to having to do things
that I think at this point, you
know, five years later, we know
that we probably want to leave
to some other tool or to some
other thing and doing it some
other way. And I think
customises has benefited from
the things that Helm had to just
deal with. Right, so Helm is
kind of like, you know, back in
my day, right, we had to walk to
school and shoes and six foot
snow and work without shoes.
It's that type of thing. I just
feel like customized has taken
has been able to take advantage
of of just being that next
iteration, I guess. I mean,
maybe that's the conclusion that
we're kind of alluding to here
between the two. But that's not
also not to say that you
shouldn't use helm. Can we? Can
I Can any of us say that, that
there isn't a use case today?
Where I
John Osborne: think I think
that's where I'm struggling to,
because Helm still has a Mac,
ball. And also kudos to the home
team for what they did with with
three, they did. A lot of that
complexity, they ripped out
Teller, they moved it all into
the, you know, into the client
side, their mood, much code, all
that stuff. So kudos to them.
But they, they do still have a
massive ecosystem of users. And
even though I use Helm when it
first came out, with helm, to
which I think one was out for
like a month or something at the
time, but it does kind of feel
like that most of the users are
not net you new users. And maybe
that's wrong, but their
ecosystem is so big. So maybe
I'd like to wish we had somebody
on the show that that just
picked a new that just picked a
new tool, and they picked him
over customized. And maybe it is
that that people and that the
templating. And maybe that
mental model just works better
for them than having
Jamie Duncan: an interesting
thought I just had as we were as
y'all were talking that through.
If I'm building an application,
and I'm the ops team, and I have
a dev team or multiple dev
teams, and I'm deploying it into
my infrastructure, I think
customized is easier, is a more
effective solution. But if I'm
sending something out to the
public, as a product, I have
Helm chart is what I would most
likely pick. And I don't think
it's just because of the size of
the ecosystem. I think those
Helm charts with the external
dependencies that I can control
as a product owner, make that
workflow a lot easier than
saying go grab some GitHub, and
here's the customized file. And
here's the variables you can
override it let's it is it is
packaging my my container native
application.
Tariq Islam: Yeah, no, maybe
maybe that maybe maybe there's
absolutely room for both, right,
because I've always looked at
customize. Something that's more
infrastructure related,
environmental related. So if I'm
trying to define to your point,
Jamie earlier, my dev
environment, my production
environment, everything in
between. and, and leverage the
overlay architecture that
customized provides me to be
able to do that at scale. That's
That's me harnessing things
right or setting up a harness.
And those are my guardrails. And
it's easy for me to do at scale,
especially in enterprises, where
there's like maybe dozens and
dozens of lines of businesses
that I've got to be able to
support. How long the other hand
would, I guess be further left,
where we're to now talking
about? Well, we, we support or
approve this specific
configuration of my sequel to be
deployed?
John Osborne: I think to Jamie
kind of touched on something and
I'm not even sure how to
articulate it. But I feel like
customize makes assumptions
about your ops team. And I think
that there's something there
with with Git Ops, where Git ops
makes assumptions that it's not
just infrastructure as code, but
your workflows revolve around
Git. And I feel like with
customize, it's making
assumptions that your ops team
has workflows that are good,
that are focused around get, and
that you're working really
closely with your dev teams,
which maybe isn't always the
case. And I don't know if I've
articulated that correctly. But
I feel like there's there's
something there with the
assumptions around customize and
how you're working. It's the
design principles. You're
Tariq Islam: right. And I think,
and I just made another
Association, as you were saying
that I I've always felt like and
I don't know, I'm just not
realizing this, but I've always
felt like Helm charts. Were very
similar to openshift templates.
Is that a fair analogy?
Unknown: Yeah.
Tariq Islam: Do you guys
remember that?
John Osborne: Yeah. So openshift
templates did have some extra
things in there. But yeah, it
was probably 80% analogous.
Tariq Islam: Just in terms of
use cases? Yeah. Not so like for
like, but just giving, giving,
you know, they didn't on the
right. And a way to give some
sort of well defined, not
necessarily catalog of thing
that's something separate No, I
think that you know, if you want
to if you want to deploy a
patchy if you want to deploy my
sequel if you want to deploy sto
if you want to deploy X, Y or Z
thing on top of this hardness or
on top of this environment that
I've configured, here is a is a
happy little is a happy Helm
chart for you to, to use. And
this is this is the baseline of
what we'll take this, these are
the guardrails around that
application
John Osborne: openshift
templates didn't really have all
that layering approach. It just
had one master template with
environment variables. And and
it could it could do some random
generation of numbers and
passwords and things like that.
But it wasn't, it wouldn't layer
on all your changes, per se.
Yeah, it
Tariq Islam: wasn't true
templates. Yeah, exactly the way
the way Helm is, but I'm
thinking just, just
functionally,
Jamie Duncan: I think you
certainly have similar feelings.
It's been a while since I used
an open ship template.
John Osborne: But yeah, the most
ops experience, Jamie, like, do
you think I was touching on
something on the assumptions?
Jamie Duncan: Yeah, no, yeah.
And I think those assumptions
like, you know, if you're facing
inward, if you're building an
internal application, you know,
if you're the ops team in a
DevOps environment, those
relationships are very different
than if you're sending your code
out to an end user.
John Osborne: Or if you're a
large enterprise that has never
met, the I've seen, never met
them before, regardless of
Jamie Duncan: what's on your
paycheck, you know, those end
users are completely different
experiences, depending on you
know, how those things are
structured. I think it's really
interesting idea, and I've
always thought of them as sort
of a linear, like an
evolutionary path. And they may
not be,
John Osborne: I'm gonna be in
the shower, and something's
gonna hit me. I'm gonna really
set articulate this. So yeah, it
does feel like a handoff. Almost
like a ticket driven handoff
versus an API driven handoff or
something.
Jamie Duncan: Yeah, that's a
good way to put it. Yeah. Yeah.
One is not less valid than the
other one. They certainly have
different use cases. Mm hmm.
John Osborne: And they both
exist, and aren't going
anywhere.
Jamie Duncan: Yes, as a neither.
God knows neither going
anywhere, anytime soon. Yeah.
Tariq Islam: Yeah, I know, we
got to wrap this up. But I just
I would love to see. I would
love to see if anyone out there
has actually leveraged both,
right? We've got plenty of
examples of folks leveraging one
or the other. But I'd love to
see a success story around. Yes,
we we've we've got the use
cases. And we've we've leveraged
both across, you know, a few
different processes between cicd
between in, you know,
infrastructures code and the
whole Git ops thing that we've
been doing. I'm sure there's
someone out there.
John Osborne: There's definitely
I've seen people online saying
that they were doing it. But I
think to me, the cognitive
overhead is now just too high.
Yeah, of what you're doing.
Jamie Duncan: You know, we
talked a lot and that, you know,
Episode 10, we'd have our first
guest. If someone does want to
weigh in there, whether you have
sort of expertise level taking
something in production into
production with both of these
tools and where you're using
them. Let us know. And come hang
out and talk for a few minutes
about make us a little smarter.
John Osborne: Always down for
always down, I get smarter.
Jamie Duncan: It rarely works
for me, but yeah, it really
works. So I think this is it's
kind of we again, we were
talking about this before we
started recording. I think we're
going to do the next few
episodes on sort of CDW
principles, sort of ci CD
concepts and where it all lives
in the Kubernetes ecosystem
right now. This was for a few
minutes. We talked about this
being the The first of those,
but we've picked it, we jumped
right into the middle. So I
think we'll start that in
earnest here in a couple of
weeks. But is there anything
else we want to we want to kick
this? Do we want to kick this
from another angle? Before we
wrap up?
Tariq Islam: I feel like we've
arrived to a point here where we
could we could confidently tell
folks that there are use cases
for both.
Jamie Duncan: Yeah, I think
we've certainly teased out a
pattern that none of us had
fully recognized before. We'd
all have pieces of it, but I've
never had the whole fault
Tariq Islam: and tools why it's
why I love this podcast with you
guys. It's always a journey of
discovery and reflection. That
fantastic tastic
John Osborne: Yep. There's about
400 projects in the CNC f
landscape for CIC D some I
definitely think we should pick
some of them that are that we
think are gaining traction or
resonating the most with
customers.
Tariq Islam: See ICD is probably
going to cover about 380 of
those. So I mean, we'll get
we'll get right to it in the
next episode.
John Osborne: Do you want to you
want to tackle DevOps to without
being too hand wavy?
Tariq Islam: Well, I just
causing me some anxiety over
here.
Jamie Duncan: You have a stay in
pain behind my left eye. Sweet
Tarik, you want to bring us you
want to close this out? I mean,
this was this was this is the
topic you wanted to cover?
Tariq Islam: Yeah. No, we we So
yeah, just to wrap it up
covered, we covered helm. And
its history in, in this space
that goes way back, I mean, way,
way back, covered its use cases
kind of its architecture and the
iterations in between. We looked
at, at customize and we we
juxtapose them, we compare and
contrast and them. And I think
the coolest thing about this
episode is I think we've all
kind of arrived at a place where
we feel like there's definitely
room for both, but it's got to
be really well thought out. So
again, if there's if there's
anyone out there that's done
this in any real way,
Jamie Duncan: we'd love to hear
from you. Very cool. Thanks for
joining us on episode 10 of K
files.
John Osborne: Thanks, everyone.
Stay safe.
Tariq Islam: Thank you.