Jamie Duncan: Yes. Hey, and
thanks for joining us on episode
11 of the K files. My name is
Jamie Duncan, I work at Google
Cloud with me all, as always is
tark Islam.
Tariq Islam: Hey everyone, tarc
Islam, also with Google Cloud,
Jamie Duncan: and john Osborne,
John Osborne: head runs is john
Osborne with Red Hat.
Jamie Duncan: JOHN is currently
enjoying a Stella Artois from
his home studio, and I'm a
little jealous of him,
John Osborne: well deserved.
Jamie Duncan: It's Tuesday, and
john said it's already been a
run. So this is not going to be
a coop con recap episode,
because I think all three of us
combined have had a chance to
watch 17 minutes of coop con
content. And since it ended last
week,
John Osborne: I tried. I don't
know what you guys, I just, it's
the whole idea of blocking out
my calendar when I'm home. And
then someone's like, I have this
really high priority thing. And
it's like, well, I'm sorry, I'm
watching YouTube, like it
doesn't, just doesn't, doesn't
really work like when you're at
it, as well as when you're
actually physically at
somewhere. So
Jamie Duncan: yeah, yeah, I've
run in I have this, I don't have
the attention span for a virtual
conference. I really don't. And
Chris short, said it pretty
well. He had a thread on
Twitter, where he's kind of
said, you know, this is my last
virtual event. And he laid out
some pretty good logic and some
stuff I didn't wholly agree
with. But I certainly understand
where it's coming from. And I
agree with the sentiment in
totality. So So no, coop con
recap. We're, I'm sure we will
find as the content gets onto
YouTube and gets out there.
Well, I plan on watching a ton
of it, there were a ton of good
talks, but so far have watched
almost none.
John Osborne: I do feel like one
thing I will say about coop con,
I do feel like in the future,
they'll probably have both modes
where you can go there. But also
it is in a good experience for
people that want to be home. And
it was cool. That was if you
wanted to stream it it was you
know, I think it was $100 or
something which you know, right.
And normally it's like $2,000 or
something like that. And plus
travel plus, travel. Yeah, all
that stuff. So at least I made
it Mark accessible to more
people. But
Jamie Duncan: yeah, making it
democratizing in that way is
really cool. But just being a
virtual event was a little too
rough.
Tariq Islam: I think it comes
down to delivery as well. I
mean, for me, just you
mentioning that travel and the
time off and the hotel stay and
then all that just exhausted me
just
Jamie Duncan: talking about it.
But we are taking on something
pretty ambitious. not going to
get into the huge chunk of it,
the short version is for the
next several episodes, we are
going to be tackling the
majority of what ci CD means in
the Kubernetes space today. And
we're still settling some of the
details. But it's going to be
five or six episodes. And we
have a question for people. And
we'll probably throw a Twitter
poll out there. JOHN will have
details on that later. But this
first episode, we're gonna get
down I think first and foremost,
we have to define what ci CD
means. I always we always, we
tend to start with definitions
here. And then we're going to
get into the backbones, the
platforms on which you can do ci
CD. And really kind of get down
into the nuts and bolts a little
bit and talk about some of the
pros and the cons and what would
we using today. So who wants to
take a stab at defining ci CD?
Tariq Islam: Let me start by
saying that in the minds of many
folks, you know, see ICD is
sometimes conflated with DevOps.
And I think it's important for
us to start defining c ICD by
first defining what it's not.
And see, ICD is definitely not
DevOps, but it certainly falls
under the auspices of DevOps. I
think I think we'll start
teasing out DevOps through the
course of these episodes.
Because they are inherently
interrelated. And again, I think
ci CD represents a subset
manifestation of a DevOps dev
sec Ops, Dev, appsec, ham
sandwich. We put it culture, but
I think, I think I think it's
important again, for the
listeners to just settle, you
know, the backdrop here is that
they are, they are very separate
topics to discuss. And with C
ICD, and how we're going to
approach it, it is about the
tools. But you know, and john
made this great point earlier.
It's also about the process
around those tools and and the
impact that all of that has on
the people. So you can start
seeing where that bleeds into
the DevOps part of it. But it's
not it's not everything. DevOps.
I know that sounds weird, but I
think it'll become clearer as we
as we go through these episodes.
John Osborne: Yeah, I mean, if I
always tell people like if
DevOps was just purely a
technical problem, it already
would have been solved, right?
The hard part is the people. But
I think at the same time, if you
look at what you can do in an
organization for most people, it
is they can automate something.
And that's why we I think, why
we end up talking about ci CD so
much, because it is a, it's more
tangible in the sense that more
people can make a difference
through automation, and some of
these some of these practices,
whereas, you know, defining
outcomes, and you know, reorg,
doing reorg is when necessary,
and some of the other cross
functional team stuff ends up
being, you know, there's only a
small number of people in
organizations that can change
some of those things that you
that ended up need to be changed
at some point. So
Jamie Duncan: yes, it sounds
like we're gonna be talking a
lot about technical debt from a
couple of different angles.
Tariq Islam: I think we have to
Yep.
Jamie Duncan: Yeah. And it's
kind of interesting. In I had
this discussion, I forget who I
was talking to whether it was on
Twitter or in like an internal
chat room or what. But um,
technical debt takes on this
negative connotation
immediately. But when you're are
doing something like john said,
when you are making these
positive changes, because if
you're a completely manual shop
that runs off with three ring
binders, and three gay and
conference calls, going to
getting into, you know,
automating your pipelines for
continuous deployment is taking
on new technical debt. And there
are good kinds of technical debt
to take on, you know, it's like,
there is, you know, there's
payday loan technical debt of
people making poor choices, and
everyone having to endure them,
you know, for a long time,
organizationally. But there's
also mortgage technical debt,
where the debt is, you know, of
a low enough interest rate to
push the to push it a little too
far. But it It provides a lot of
benefit for what you're taking
the dead on for, and ci CD, a CD
platform. Most of the time,
unless it's just a really poor
implementation is good technical
debt to take on.
John Osborne: Yeah, I think too,
like, you know, talking about
technical debt. You think about
agile and some other things that
also, you know, there's a Venn
diagram somewhere out there, but
that get entwined with things
like ci CD sometimes in Sprint's
and these things, and there is
almost this feeling out there. I
think that's honestly probably
justified that a lot of times,
we get so focused on features
that we're not adequately
prioritizing. I'm totally gonna
go off the rails in this
episode. But we're not prior,
we're not prioritizing our
technical debt and our testing
and good architecture diagrams
and documentation and those
things because you start doing
two week sprints and things like
that it gets it does get, if you
do that poorly, it actually can
be worse than waterfall if you
don't actually start. You know,
prioritizing things the way they
should. And I will say to for as
a side tangent, we'll put it in
the show notes, there's a new
really good book out called
project to product on a flow
framework. It's this kind of
prescriptive plan for value
stream management. And the the
author also spoke at the DevOps
enterprise summit, He's really
good. I've never tried this, but
just reading it and in watching
it, it makes sense and resonated
with me a little bit in terms
of, you know, how much should
you how much of your Sprint's
should you focus on things like
reducing your technical debt and
new features? And what makes and
when should you adjust that and
why and it all sort of made
sense to me? Yeah, I
Jamie Duncan: mean, the
traditional, you know, the old
trope is that features drive
revenue. But even with
Kubernetes, we've gotten to the
point where like cube one died,
18 was very much a bug fix
release, there were very few new
features, very few things moved
from alpha to beta, or beta to
GA. And like you're talking
about john, like, when you're in
these two week sprints, you can
fixate on the wrong things, and
really drive your product into
an unhealthy state.
Tariq Islam: So I guess then,
the goal of properly done CIC D
is to avoid, you know,
forgetting the forest. Right,
and only focusing on the trees.
Yeah. And that's, and I like
your call out about technical
debt, Jamie. But I do I do have
a recent story. Actually, I was
working with an organization
that they were still packaging
up now actually, to this day,
they are still packaging up
their, their binaries in a zip
folder and emailing them to
their ops team for deployment.
John Osborne: I've seen that all
the time. So
Tariq Islam: yeah, it was Yeah,
John Osborne: I just moving it
around, you know.
Jamie Duncan: Not even SFTP
Yeah, not even.
Tariq Islam: Yeah, I see that
all the time. So but but that's
where folks are right. And I
think i think i think CIC D it
to John's point, it really does
require a cultural shift just
like Kubernetes adoption does
that we've talked about before.
I mean, this is we're talking
about not just automation to
solve problems, but this is this
is, you know, organizational
infrastructure that you're going
to build on top of.
John Osborne: I'm really getting
off the rails In this episode,
by the way, I feel will
Jamie Duncan: keep you on track,
we'll keep you on
John Osborne: Kubernetes like
actually makes a lot of sense
here. And there's other
technologies too, but you know,
it's, we talk about, I think,
Craig Mcluckie talked about this
like last year, but you know,
the move from ticket driven to
API driven well, instead of
putting in a ticket for saying
you need, what storage and how
many replicas you want, you
know, that can be part of the
API that developers hand over to
operations teams where they can
say, here's my deployment, I
need, I need, you know, this
persistent volume and need to
run this number of replicas
within this.
Tariq Islam: So that's an
interesting point. Because
Because I don't think there's a
singular formula for ci CD. I
mean, there's like, okay, build
your app, run your test, create
your artifact, you know, deploy
to staging, you know, yada yada,
yada deploy to production,
Canary, whatever, and then
you're good to go. But that can
manifest itself in many
different ways, where different
organizations define the lines
between their teams differently.
And I've seen ci CD work where
developers are reaching over to
the right, where they are
dealing with, you know, API
driven requests, or that that
engagement pattern is definitely
something that I've seen work,
but it requires a lot of, I
think, a high degree of maturity
that most probably don't have.
Jamie Duncan: And there's a
there's a pretty important
distinction as well, that I want
to draw in to try to segue this
into talking about sort of how
you get started, like talking
like using target customer, you
know, whose zip file, you know,
emailing zip files, to ops
people to deploy to deploy new
versions of things. Were john,
where you pointed out, you see
the principles and Kubernetes
very much our peanut butter and
jelly kind of scenario,
chocolate and peanut butter.
Apparently, peanut butter goes
with everything, really. But
Tariq Islam: it really including
me, oh, by the way, believe it
or not,
Jamie Duncan: yeah, I've seen
it, and not in that camp. But
let's just take a second to
recognize the universal love of
peanut butter. But there, the
there is a big difference,
because like you can't be a
little bit Kubernetes, you can
be a little bit pregnant. Once
you stand up a Kubernetes
cluster. To deploy an
application effectively, you've
got to do all of it, you've got
to containerize it, you've got
to figure out config maps,
you've got to get your ingress
and your networking and your
storage squared away, you can't
do a little bit of Kubernetes,
you don't have to put all of
your applications on Kubernetes.
But to do our application on
cube, you got to do it all the
way. CDs a little different,
because that team that is you
know, receiving zip files in
their inbox to do to run a
maintenance event. They can
start down a road and and CD
principals can be taken on one
or five at a time. And all of
them provide benefit. You don't
have to go from zero to 100,
like you do with an app in coop.
You can build it up over time
and drive that adoption drive
those cultural changes with the
tooling.
Tariq Islam: And that's a good
point. Because I think that
that's why I've we have seen
organizations adopt c ICD far
before, or long before they
adopt Kubernetes in that
holistic way. Right. And by the
way, I'm totally stealing that
whole you can't be a little bit
pregnant.
Jamie Duncan: Oh, you never
heard that before.
Tariq Islam: I've never heard
that one before.
John Osborne: Oh, are you
serious? I've never get around
it for a long
Tariq Islam: time. Michelle, I'm
sheltered. What can you say?
Jamie Duncan: Poor little Tarik,
John Osborne: you're a nice boy.
I'm telling you, man. I'm
Tariq Islam: a nice boy, you
know.
Jamie Duncan: So let's, let's
talk a little bit about some of
the options. You know, this
first episode we want to talk
about the definitions. Before we
get to that I want to get into a
little bit of trivia with you
too. And I it's one of those
that where I'm wondering if I if
I was sheltered back in the day,
when the first place I was at
that was doing anything
resembling a CI CD workflow, and
they were doing it really
poorly. But I didn't know any
better at the time. It was
continuous integration.
Continuous Delivery, was what ci
CD stood for. Apparently now
it's continuous integration,
continuous deployment.
Tariq Islam: I think that's
still debatable.
Jamie Duncan: Is it so is
delivery Am I am I the only is
that like this. Sinbad being the
genie in the movie thing? Yeah.
John Osborne: Just you know,
deployment to multiple I guess
if you're saying delivering it.
I think it I think they changed
it when they started. The
delivery started happening to
me. multiple targets. And okay,
then they just started moving
into deployment. That was kind
of my, my take on it.
Tariq Islam: I'm still a fan of
delivery. Actually, I feel like
it's a little bit more generic.
Jamie Duncan: And I wonder if I
wonder if there was like a book
written. I wonder if there's, I
wonder if there are camps here
and we don't know about it.
There are some blogs that talk
about the difference between
delivery and deployment. I'll be
honest with you,
Tariq Islam: I don't think it
matters.
John Osborne: I remember the
first time that that's our it's
like,
Jamie Duncan: Reddit hated it.
John Osborne: The first
organization I worked for that
did this. I was the first few
years I was in the industry. I
just wrote code by myself in a
in in isolation, and Tareq. And
I were joking about a month ago
about how ahead some of these
people are they're like,
speaking on stage at cube con
and stuff for over them. We were
but the first organization I
went to that actually did
anything like see ICD, honestly,
I, I was very probably immature.
And I wasn't used to doing all
these things. And I remember I
went down to this, this guy's
desk, and he's like, yeah, you
know, we're gonna, we're gonna
check our code. And every night,
we're gonna scan it with a run
these tests, if things break,
we're gonna email you right
away. And I just remember
thinking, chill out, man. I just
want to write some code. I don't
want emails every night with
things breaking, because things
always break. And you know, I
didn't, I didn't actually see
later I moved into ops. And so I
kind of saw all of why that
mattered. But when I was just in
that writing code mindset, I
didn't really didn't see, at
that time, at least, while that
stuff was so important.
Jamie Duncan: I remember getting
all of those alerts. And they
were constant. And they were
useless, because they were
poorly configured. Because we
had no clue what we were doing.
And they just became white
noise. And you ignored them.
That's,
John Osborne: that's what
happens still happens. There is
no technology that solves that
problem. I do think you need to
there's a, there's just the data
you got to put the time in.
Tariq Islam: It's a it's a it's
a maturity thing, right. It's an
organization learning about what
it cares about, in terms of
delivering features and
functions. It gets better over
time. But I think, and john, I
think you mentioned this before
we started up, you know, how you
measure your ci CD pipelines,
your automation infrastructure,
that's, that's hugely important.
And you're not going to get it
right the first time, you're not
going to get it right, the
eighth time, you might get it
right, maybe the 18th time. But
I think it's, it's part of that,
that ci CD journey. And you have
to have the patience and the
discipline to kind of stick with
it, and get to a point where
it's not just about the
efficiency of the automation,
but the the data that you're
getting back. Is it useful? And
is it? Is it making your
processes better? Is it
impactful?
John Osborne: I mean, the
general kind of pattern I see
is, organizations that, you
know, initially, they really
just talk about inputs, you
know, we've got to, we've got to
do cloud, we've got to do agile,
you know, we've got to, we've
got we need the Kubernetes,
given the Kubernetes. And then,
you know, once they get a little
more mature, they start looking
at the outputs, like the, you
know, the four key metrics from
the state of DevOps reports, the
number of incidents, those
things, and then once the few
organizations have had that have
gotten pretty mature, we'll talk
about outcomes. So you know,
reducing costs and improving
operations teams and those types
of things that actually make
more of a difference. But
initially, it's like, you know,
we've got a, we need the cloud.
I mean, it'd be the cloud. And
but measurements do become
really important, I think, in
general to, to understanding
success.
Tariq Islam: So this, this begs
the question, then, you know,
what, what is it good? What is
it good ci CD infrastructure
look like beyond just build
test? stage, deploy, monitor.
John Osborne: So before Jamie
answers to like, let me just
throw, let me just throw
everything we did in the, in the
pre, the pre call of the window,
cuz I want to bring something
up, see if this resonates with
you guys. But there is a really
good article on scaling to
100,000 users, where they this,
I'll put it in the show notes.
And it's nothing to do with ci
CD. But I thought we could
actually use a similar format
for this episode is based off
what Sam and Jamie say, kind of
jog my memory, but they kind of
talked about, you know, building
something with one user on one
machine and then going into 10
users and you split up the
database and then 100 users and
then building up like, maybe we
do want to work that way for a
CI CD, or we're talking about
you know, if it's Let's just eat
what should you do and kind of
build out to what is like a
large enterprise, but what
should they be doing? Because I
do think that the answer
differs.
Jamie Duncan: Yeah, if it's just
me, my Git commits are going to
be purely curse words.
John Osborne: You can't look at
my I have nothing. I have no
documentation on code.
Jamie Duncan: Right.
Documentation will not exist.
Yeah. I think I like the idea of
starting with one person. I
don't think it's particularly
practical. He's you. It's one of
those, you know, it's a Dilbert
joke.
Tariq Islam: You know, we're
like, have you started working
yet? And no, I've spent seven
days configuring My environment.
But but but let's go back to
that example of of the
organization that still sending
zip files in an email to the SIS
ops team that probably started
with a single person somewhere.
Yeah, sure. All right. And they
didn't try to scale around that.
I think that's a good approach.
John Osborne: I think what
happens when you see those
things a lot of times is the
hire at the top of the
organizations don't have any
idea who's talking to each
other. And so what happens is,
is on the ground floor, you
know, they needed to get this to
the operations teams, and no one
really thought about silos
talking to each other. So how do
you contact someone, especially,
you know, all these things
process around for 20 years? So
how did you how did you get
something similar? 20 years ago,
you emailed it right? And so
nobody really cared to focus on
doing an improvement of that. So
here we are, was, that's still
our problem. Years later, yeah,
20 years later. Still,
Tariq Islam: I think I think one
of the best ways to distill this
maybe is is looking at Conway's
Law, perhaps because I think
cicd flies in the face of that a
little bit. where, you know,
Conway's Law states that an
organization is doomed or
destined, pick your word of
choice there to to create
systems and software that mimic
the communication patterns of
their, of their organization.
See, ICD is at least properly
done is actually meant to break
that or improve upon that. And I
think that's, that's what makes
it hard to get right. But to
Jamie's point, there are areas
of ci and CD, particularly on
the CI CD part where actually on
both sides, where you can, you
can cherry pick a little bit on
what you want to improve upon
before taking a bigger bite. And
so I think I think, you know, if
an organization wants to do
things better, it's a great
place to start. It's a it's a
good path of least resistance.
And and once you really get
really good at C, ICD and
automation, I think, I think
appetites increase for more
advanced tooling and platforms,
you know, Kubernetes, and the
like.
Jamie Duncan: So let's talk
about getting started a little
bit, because you have to, you
know, see the end, we were
talking a little bit about this,
before we hit the record button,
CD is the tooling. And, you
know, that's really where the
the sort of the line of
demarcation begins, but between
defining ci CD and defining
DevOps, and they are very
knitted together, but see ICD
very much represent a toolset
that you've adopted to get work
done. Whereas DevOps is much
more philosophy. If you're
adopting, taking that idea of
torrox example of the company
that sends a zip file for over
email for deployment jobs. If
the, if the visionary in that
group, we're starting to build
out some sort of CD pipeline,
they would have to start with an
engine, they would have to start
with a whatever you want to call
it a backbone, a platform, an
engine to begin to integrate the
CD steps. And it's that's the
first step they have to get on
top of they have to take that
first step up.
Tariq Islam: Yeah, and and I'll
go ahead and call this first one
out. And but before I call it
out, I am going to call back to
a previous episode when we were
talking about remember when we
talked about how Helm benefited
from being kind of first to
land, and then being shoehorned
for a number of use cases that
aren't so great anymore? Right.
I think that's that's where a
lot of people landed with
Jenkins. Jenkins has been around
forever. And it's a build
server. Right? It it since
inception. And it's a very good
one. But it's, it was almost
purely ci and because of its
pluggable architecture, it
became, for a long time the de
facto choice and I guess even to
this day, it's still kind of is
despite it, there being you
know, hundreds of other options
out there. It's just so so
ubiquitous,
John Osborne: it's a good point
because I think if you look at
Jenkins is there's there's
there's a lot to be said about
it but I think similar to home
and you make a good point is
that it's it's the community of
plugins and things that are
already out there I can go on to
Jenkins and build something out
in an hour that plugs to my
Slack channel and does all these
things because those plugins
exist and they're easy to
integrate and so it's definitely
not a what I would consider like
a cloud native build system but
it there's so much there that
you can reuse out of the box
that it we don't prefer that you
use at Red Hat we don't prefer
that use Jenkins but we get it
if if if that's where you end up
landing
Jamie Duncan: Yeah, the copy
paste ability of Jenkins once
you have something built, you're
able to duplicate it quickly and
enhance because what you find in
a because it does very much
mimic your communication And
patterns, most of your
applications deploy in a similar
way. Once you get the first one
figured out, you know the first
pill cost a million dollars a
second pill cost a nickel. Once
you get that first pipeline
built out, you can reference it
and just make the needed
modifications to build out a
pretty mature Jenkins
environment. I deployed Jenkins
Actually, this morning, just to
look because I hadn't looked at
Jenkins in a long time I
deployed it into a Kubernetes
cluster. And the process was
pretty good. You know, so I took
on, I said, you know, when we
were planning this first episode
out, I said, I would deploy
Jenkins and Spinnaker, and then
add a Jenkins X to it this
morning when I was when I was
tinkering around. Have those
three? Jenkins is the most
straightforward thing to deploy.
Was it a Helm chart? Yeah, of
course, it was.
Tariq Islam: I knew it.
John Osborne: Jenkins feels so
2005. But it does Oh my god, it
is.
Jamie Duncan: Like, it's, I'm
stunned it how like, it's soon
Alright, so to deploy Jenkins,
your there's a little bit of
ammo, it needs a service account
inside the coop cluster. You
create a namespace, create a
service account, run a Helm
chart, and your cluster is up
and running takes three minutes,
I logged into that thing. And I
was immediately in 2009. And the
only differences in the UI that
I can ascertain after like a 10
minute analysis was they've made
the font smaller. And the
graphics were updated about six
like they it's like they took
the kitchen from 1998. And they
painted the cabinets white and
put down new countertops. But
it's the exact same kitchen
Tariq Islam: felt like coming
home.
Jamie Duncan: Oh, like, like
coming in back to the you know
the step dad that you never
really liked them. But they're
very straightforward to deploy
into a Kubernetes cluster and
took advantage. Like once it had
that service account. It did
populate stuff. So like it was
running builds inside the coop
cluster, it was doing everything
pretty effectively, pretty
quickly. But I'm just like it
was 12 years ago, when you click
new pipeline, you know, no
matter which option you pick
whether it was one of the pre
canned ones, or the DIY one. It
was 74 radio buttons, 92,
checkboxes, and every one of
them brought up for other
questions you had to answer. And
at the bottom was a text area
that I wrote my shell script in?
Yeah, it is. And it was I was
like, Oh, my it like the
workflow. And I guess at that
point, because it is so
ubiquitous, it's rate of
evolution has to be incredibly
slow. It's the generic general
purpose, right? The old server,
everyone uses it. So everyone's
holding on to the way they're
currently using it. I feel
really sorry for cloudbees you
know, the people that do it
professionally?
John Osborne: Yeah, there's
something to that too. Because
if you look at the a lot of the
way, you know, in practice, at
least what I've seen, tell me if
you've seen this, but when
people get hired as a quote
unquote DevOps engineer, what
they end up doing is just
writing a lot of glucose, and
that glucose ends up often
living as custom shell scripts
inside of Jenkins. Yeah, and
yeah, that's a hard place to
live in, I think,
Jamie Duncan: yeah. It reminded
It reminds me a lot of like, the
way pivotal stuff works. reminds
me a lot of the way I did jobs
1213 years ago,
Tariq Islam: I will say that,
you know, I'm a fan of knocking
on Jenkins, but for, for the,
for the for the listeners. And I
still think that if if it does
end up being Jenkins that you do
go with as your you're kind of
getting started stepping stone,
so be it right. And if that's
what that's what you're used to
get good with ci CD and
automation and getting, getting
to a better place. Go for it.
Now, that said, You are
absolutely going to hit, you
know, major issues with respect
to scaling. You know, Jenkins is
not exactly friendly to
resources. But that's something
that that's something
John Osborne: you might care
about day one.
Jamie Duncan: Yeah. And like you
said, starting at one user, it
works just fine. Mm hmm. Yeah,
yeah. It really scaling up in
102,000. I mean, let's all you
know, I freely admit that the
modern internet owns lens, a
large portion of its existence
to Jenkins, is you can't get
that much software deployed
manually. We would still be
working on your stuff from seven
years ago. We all have benefited
from Jenkins globally as a
product that said, it's like
Domino's Pizza. It is not the
best pizza in the town you live
in, but it's going to show up
pretty consistently better than
they're going. Right, exactly.
They're going to be there in a
half hour and you're going to
eat it. Yeah. It's not the best
pizza on the planet. You can get
a better experience. But, but
you're going to pay for it and
you're going to have to jump
through some hoops to get it. So
one of those better experiences.
So what Jenkins ended up doing a
few years ago, and I don't know
exactly when. But Jenkins then
is, is there and it has a sort
of glacial evolutionary path,
you know, because everyone's
using it. No one wants it to
change. So what they did was
make a thing called Jenkins x.
It was back when I think putting
x in front of at the end of
things was cool. That was
actually a team that left Red
Hat to, to go build that. And if
you remember, was it. Yep. It
was. Oh, yeah. Yeah, not.
John Osborne: So. And it wasn't
the same Jenkins team. It was a
bunch of people that were really
strong and on messaging and kind
of middleware. Some of the
people that worked on are built
Apache camel, those types of
people, and they left and did
their own thing. And they came
up with Jenkins x.
Jamie Duncan: Yep. So Jenkins X
has a great UI for Kubernetes
ties itself into octant, which
is a really solid user
experience. There's an ops
persona panel for for Jenkins x,
there's a dev persona panel for
Jenkins x, really slick, really
modern, get a lot of work done
really efficiently. So I think
under the covers, it's using a
lot of the same state engine
tooling. It's a lot of the same
engine of Jenkins, but it's
presented in a more modern
fashion. And it's got more
modern hooks, like there's a
more modern API that you can
interact with, and really deal
with the tooling much more in a
much more modern cloud native
way. deploying it to some of the
silly stuff I've ever seen in my
life, I cannot figure out the
lot. The logic of how they came
up with the deployment tooling
for Jenkins x. It starts out
really cool. It starts out easy.
Like it's like 10 lines of JSON,
that you drop into a terraform
template, and you run terraform
in it and terraform apply. And
then it checks out a repository
and it does Oh, no, then it does
some stuff. So it actually
deploys a Kubernetes cluster on
your cloud provider. So like you
tell them in that in that JSON,
you tell it what cloud project
you're using in different ones,
like AWS looks a lot different
than Google Cloud, all that. But
it stands up a Kubernetes
cluster, and in that Kubernetes
clusters running just about
nothing, then you have to go
download another binary, called
j X on your local machine, run a
couple of more commands, one of
which checks out a repository
from GitHub. And then that
generates a yamo file that you
run another command on that
thing goes and sticks the right
things in the Kubernetes cluster
that you deployed 20 minutes
previously.
John Osborne: I say felted, just
when you're explaining, Yeah,
Jamie Duncan: dude, I and
John Osborne: I looked at
Jenkins x when I first started
that company. So I was
interested in what they were
doing. But I haven't really
followed it much the last couple
years.
Jamie Duncan: I don't understand
how they got there. And the fun
thing is I pull down the latest
version of everything. There is
some hardware inside some of
that. And it's all terraform
under the covers the deployment
tooling inside some of the
terraform, or inside some of the
file somewhere inside this JSX
binary, it is hard coded to look
to check out the master from
when it checks out this GitHub
repo, and the master branch
doesn't exist anymore. And
GitHub because they renamed it
to Maine, but the installer
hasn't been updated. And I
pulled down the latest release
binary to try it out for like
three different versions. So the
installer for Jenkins x is
effectively broken right now.
Tariq Islam: So this is where
managing your own
infrastructure. And the type of
infrastructure you choose. As
soon as you get beyond a small
team really starts to matter. I
Jamie Duncan: think so yeah. So
when we were sketching this,
this episode out, we broke down
three generic categories of CD
backbone CD platforms, Jenkins
and Spinnaker would be the
number two one, but we're not
talking to so Jenkins and
chicken neck Spinnaker, and I'm
sure there are others are what
you would call traditional. And
those are the you know, I'm
going to deploy a thing and
whether it's deployed into
Kubernetes or deployed into a VM
or wherever. It's a traditional
application, and I get a
traditional experience from it.
The second type C FCD. backbone
is one that's a little more
cloud native. And is tark. is do
you want to get into that a
little bit.
Tariq Islam: Yes, so the cloud
native ones, some some examples
here. But this is by no means an
exhaustive list. In fact, this
is probably 1% of everything
that's out there, you know,
tools like circle ci, GitHub
actions, git lab, ci, Travis CI,
I think of those really comes
out to, you know, GitHub and get
lab being the more popular ones.
I've seen more folks, I've
actually seen quite a lot of Git
lab.
Jamie Duncan: Yeah, it's really
good. I used it a lot. We used
it a lot at VMware. really
effective. Travis and circle I
think they were they were first
to market in this space. And I
don't know who be who. But
Travis and circle, were filling
the gap before get lab and
GitHub had their own integrated
CD
Tariq Islam: platform. For my
own edification, how are we
differentiating between
traditional and cloud native? Is
it just how many years old they
are? Or deployment model? Maybe
both? What makes a thing cloud
native in this context?
John Osborne: I mean, I think,
you know, if you look at tecton,
or some of the newer ways to
build pipelines, it's that they
can one be event driven, in the
sense that, you know, something
can trigger the pipeline to
start or even instantiate from
scratch, right? And then, you
know, does it run well, in
containers? Can you scale up
scale down? Very easily? You
know, is it a lot of times now,
we're also talking about is it
declarative in the sense that
you set what the desired state
is going to be? And not just the
steps to get there an imperative
model? But it's, you know, is it
going to run on Kubernetes?
Well, is it going to run as a
container? Well, those are the
types of things that I that I
normally think about, I will say
to like, before, before I
forget, you know, I think when
we talk about building, in a
pipeline, any sort of scale like
and I would even say, once you
get to like 10 nodes, if you're
building in your cluster, you
probably want a dedicated
machine just for the builds,
because that he comes so spiky,
that it really can destroy some
of your, your, your node
resource usage, you know, things
can spike up really high spike
back down, especially if you're
doing Java, you know, start
doing Maven builds or even node
j s, you know, Mo the NPM stuff.
You know, even go right, because
it's it's statically compiled.
So the builds tend to be pretty
compute resource intensive
first, but obviously, the
runtime is very good, right. So
you know, you probably at any
sort of even medium scale, you
probably want to look to start
to have dedicated machines that
just do builds. This sounds
Tariq Islam: a lot like the
problems that we've seen
organizations run into with,
with Jenkins, right, is resource
contention spike Enos having to
have dedicated infrastructure, I
think, you know, I don't know,
maybe maybe cloud native is not
the most accurate term for this
category, maybe it's the fact
that the design principles, the
user experience, in these kind
of Next Gen. backbone, backbones
are, are just better, you know,
a little bit more refined.
Jamie Duncan: And I'm thinking
through, because I think I was
the one that wrote cloud native
in the outline, so I'll take the
hit for that one.
John Osborne: Actually, I didn't
even see that.
Jamie Duncan: But I'm gonna hold
on to I'm not gonna let go of it
just yet. Because john tark, I
think you're 100% on point is
that they are an evolution and
how it works. The ones that we
the ones that we've taught that
we've sort of enumerated circle
and Travis and get lab and get
hubs integrated ones, and there
are a ton more and a ton of them
are very platform specific, like
natla, fly and a bunch of
others. Even if you're deploying
get lab on prem, and you do have
to account for those build
resources. When I'm hooking Mike
a Kubernetes, cluster into those
build resources, it takes me
about 30 seconds. And the entire
experience is driven through the
Git lab UI. And I effectively
just give Git lab permissions to
go deploy workloads on my
cluster. And I can drop it into
a namespace with quotas and
handle those resources that way.
So we're Git lab, because it has
an on prem version is almost a
hybrid between a traditional and
a cloud native. You do account
for that to some degree with
with Jenkins. And I've actually
ran in or give with Git lab. And
I've actually ran into that
where, you know, my build server
ran out of resources a lot. It
was some projects I worked on at
VMware. But with like GitHub,
and Travis and circle, they're
all as a service. So you don't
have to provide any of you don't
have to account for any of it.
And the worst case scenario is
that you're waiting a little
while longer on your build to
run if it's eating up a lot of
stuff, or if the run queue is
just long with GitHub actions
or, you know, in the Travis CI,
Travis is handling all that for
you or circle ci is handling all
that for you.
John Osborne: They've done a
really good job. Some of those
tools were Oh man,
Jamie Duncan: they are awesome.
John Osborne: They used to be a
Git repo and now their ci CD
workflows. thinly disguised as a
Git repo a Git repo. Yeah. But
they've done a good job for
sure.
Jamie Duncan: Yeah. And the cool
thing about all of these is the
way they present themselves to
the user. And it's kind of the
reason I'm holding on to cloud
native as them as a moniker for
them. Because all of them have
the same workflow. Whereas
Jenkins, you've got to go into
the Jenkins UI to find these
things, you know, define a
pipeline to get all this stuff
hammered out all these buttons
and checkboxes and text fields.
With all of the cloud native
tools that we've talked that we
just mentioned, all of them are
a single YAML file at the base
of your repository. And that
your entire experience. That
means that it's massively
powerful. It is Yep. And that's
what that's why I'm holding on
to cloud native, because if I
drop a YAML, dot, Travis, ci dot
YAML, at the top of my repo, and
I tell Travis that you have
permissions to talk to this
repo, and I'm done.
Tariq Islam: So this begs the
question, then is it worth, you
know, whether it's the
organization that's still
emailing their zip files? Or
maybe it's another organization
that's slightly more mature than
that, or retelling them? Or we
issue like a peanut butter
spread? Going back with peanut
butter here?
Jamie Duncan: Are we just
telling everyone always goes
back to penguin?
Tariq Islam: are we telling
folks, you know, just go
straight for the, the what we're
calling cloud native, like the
circle ci, and the Travis CI is
and get labs of the world? And
skipping over, over Jenkins? And
just maybe, are we saying that
Jenkins is just legacy enough?
That you can you can you can
forget about it and move into
these newer tools?
John Osborne: I think it
depends. Because if you look at,
you know, cloud native stuff,
right, you know, you has all its
dependencies with it kind of
handles restarts, well, you
know, it can run on containers,
Kubernetes, it's highly
available, all that stuff. You
know, that requires in some
cases, you know, so you're using
tecton, as an example, right. So
you might have to write
containers with automation in it
to make some of this stuff
happen that you might have a
plugin out of the box with
Jenkins. So it's, it is kind of
a your mileage may vary,
depending on your use case, but
and not every org has people
just sitting around that are
writing Glue Code in containers,
to do all this stuff. So it's
kind of a, you know, you have to
make your own decision. But I do
think that there's a certain
amount of technical debt you
assume by by doing Greenfield
Jenkins deployments at this
point.
Jamie Duncan: Yeah. And I think
at least for me, I see them as
a, it's a case coverage problem
is circle and Travis and GitHub
and get lab, they all have some
limitations. If you're going to
use Travis or circle, or just
about any of them, I think
you're going to be in the
limitations aren't great. But
you're going to have to use some
of their tooling. And they're
going to make some assumptions
about what you're doing. And the
steps are going to be relative
or somewhat limited compared to
what you can do in Travis, or
what you can do in Jenkins,
where you know, the world is
your is your checkbox. If you
find yourself straining against
those limitations be because of
the way you've designed your
application, or because of the
limitations or security needs
you've got. You always have
Jenkins available as this
infinitely customizable platform
that's going to get you where
you need to go. But for that
problem, I don't know if it's
85, or 97 and a half. But for a
very high percentage of modern
applications being written
today. These cloud native CD
tools, fit your use case very
comfortably, and are a much
lower barrier to entry into this
arena.
Tariq Islam: And I will say that
of these, or at least of the
ones that I've seen, I think I
think Git lab is probably the
furthest along as far as
bringing together feature set
ease of use deployment pattern.
You know it? Again, to your
point, Jamie, it's not it's not
100%. As far as customizability
the way Jenkins is, but I think
I think for the vast majority of
organizations, they've I'm
calling them out because you
know, they've done great work.
Jamie Duncan: Yeah, I agree. I
like I said, I use it pretty
extensively at VMware, and have
used it on and off before and
after. And I'd agree, yeah, they
are the most mature of all the
cloud native ci, CD tooling. And
it is very easy to use.
Tariq Islam: So let's talk about
this this last category that
we've got here, managed, right
and managed by managed and the
most sensitive to this term.
Because I think there's a lot of
confusion around it. Anything
for me, and we I don't I don't
want to make this a rat hole.
But when I say manage I'm
talking about, you are not
deploying this infrastructure or
this tool in any way, shape or
form where you're having to
manage it. Right? There's no
such thing as day to operations
here. This is a purely Oh
serverless for form of, of ci CD
infrastructure, where you just
kind of click on a button. And
and you get a thing. Yeah.
Jamie Duncan: Right. Yeah, I see
them is in the what we're trying
to talk the examples of what
we're talking about her, like
AWS code pipeline, Google's
cloud build, we couldn't come up
with azures, I think they've
called it Azure DevOps. Yeah,
it's their builds that
John Osborne: it's that that the
TFS, the Team Foundation Server
stuff in Azure called Azure
DevOps.
Jamie Duncan: Yeah. And really
what you get as you get a pretty
configurable set of inputs. And
you get a completely abstracted
build experience, and you get a
less configurable set of
destinations or output of what
it will what it will generate
for you and where it will put
it. But that's really it, you
feed it your source code, you
feed it some parameters, it does
some magic, and it drops the
result of that magic in one of a
handful of locations.
Tariq Islam: So I think this
one, this category is pretty
interesting, because I feel like
it is the most scalable from one
to 100,000, just because of the
nature of how its deployed, you
know, at least from the
perspective of the user, it's
not something that's deployed.
But you know, me as an
individual, I can use Cloud
build, for example, or Azure
DevOps for just my own purposes.
And then I could bring any of
these into a fully fledged
enterprise organization, and use
them at scale as well. Now, you
know, you do have to consider
which one of these you're going
to pick, because the one that
you pick, is is going to is
going to effectively tie you to
a cloud. Right, but, but i think
i think i think listeners
should, you know, see the
advantages of a managed offering
here, because of how quickly you
can get up and running, and how
quickly you're able to scale and
bring it to the rest of an
organization. But, again, you
know, going back to the point
that Jamie made around technical
debt, there's something to
consider.
John Osborne: So for my
consistency, what you'll see
from adoption, but in my
opinion, like ci CD tools in the
cloud, is managed services have
some of the lowest adoption of
all the public cloud provider
services. And I don't know, but
I think the reason for that is
is, is people have a really hard
time paying to build their code.
There's some there must be some
psychology there, I don't know.
But pay as you go. And
obviously, you pay with, if you
manage anything yourself, you
you pay to, in terms of in terms
of all the people that you that
are managing those things,
right. But it's not as apparent
as paying for a service. And I
see challenges with with people
just mentally getting over that
hurdle of paying to compile my
code. Have you seen that or such
as something that that, that
I've seen?
Tariq Islam: I've actually not
seen that yet. Although, again,
I do, I would have to agree with
you that it's, it's not it,
there hasn't been a huge wave of
adoption across these tools. But
I can, I can see, I can see why
that would be prevalent. It's
one of those. It's one of those,
like, you know, I'm going to do
it myself kind of thing. It's,
it's this is low value task. And
and that's the that's the
perception, right, that the
tasks of building, you know,
compiling, building, you know,
all of that, all that sci fi
stuff, especially, is deemed low
level. machinery. And, and and
it's Yeah, I can, I can totally
get there.
Jamie Duncan: Yeah, my take on
it was, I certainly agree that
it's not, you know, people
aren't beating down the doors to
Google Cloud to use Cloud build.
It's a great tool, and it does
exactly what it needs to do. But
it's it's very much a value add
for someone who is sort of all
in on AWS cloud, at least in the
public cloud space. I assumed
that slower curve of adoption
was because people have
relatively mature CD pipelines
because like we said, the
beginning people have been doing
this for a long time. So if
they've got something and it's
not broke, They don't see it as
debt, they see it as providing
value. Why would they read? You
know, why would they build
cycles to change it? And as you
were talking, I started
wondering if that is if it's
that as much, or if it's is, as
we were looking at these and
talking about them, you know, as
you go from these traditional
platforms like Jenkins, to these
cloud native platforms like Git
lab, to these managed platforms,
like like AWS code pipeline,
each step along the way, you
have to have good, better
hygiene. Like you can do some
crazy woolly stuff inside
Jenkins and get your application
to build.
John Osborne: Yeah, automation
is hard. I mean,
Jamie Duncan: yeah, exactly.
Like we said at the beginning,
but and there's lots of duct
tape is strong.
John Osborne: Yeah. Duct Tape
survival solutions, sometimes
Exactly. Oh, yeah.
Jamie Duncan: And Jenkins is
really good duct tape. It's the
duct tape of the internet. It is
needed. Yeah, the cloud native
tools, you can use a little less
duct tape, you have to have a
little better hygiene, there are
some more limitations. And the
Manage platforms, there are even
more limitations. Like I said,
you have a more limited set of
inputs, you have a more limited
set of outputs. And you don't
have a lot of control of what
happens in the middle. So I
wonder if it's because they're
just they have something they're
happy with? Or it's because
they've got their house of cards
duct taped up enough that they
don't want to touch it. That is
that sort of limiting some of
that, that that adoption of
these managed platforms? I don't
know, it's kind of an open ended
question. I'm thinking about it,
you know, even as I say it out
loud. But I'm, we're running a
little long here. Yeah, talking
about this. So john, do you want
to give us give the skinny on
what we're going to do for the
next five or six episodes, yes,
and throw this idea out for
John Osborne: free. I will throw
this out there too, before we
get into the agenda. But, you
know, we talked a little bit
early on before we hit the
record button about about
DevOps. And if it's even
something that would would
resonate with the users here.
You know, it's DevOps in
practice ends up being kind of a
collection of practices and
methodologies around product
flow. You know, things are out
there's a lot of people and
process side to it. And so, you
know, with, would you be
interested in the audience of
listening to practices that
work, don't work around, you
know, moving things like
institutionalized codified
processes into automation, or
how to what works and doesn't
work with things like cross
functional teams, ways that you
can avoid common pitfalls that
we see in organizations, those
types of things? Or are you
mostly focused, we'll put a
Twitter poll out, you can email
us as well, or DMS, whatever.
But or you just focused on the
tooling. And you want us to just
kind of stick with the more I
guess, tangible things in
technology, you know, that's a,
we're gonna leave that up to
you. If there's, if there's
interest, we'll do it. If not,
we'll just we'll skip over it.
But I think the next episode,
we're gonna go into ci, and some
of the things from a depth
perspective, like code quality
and testing and registries and
some of the open source projects
that are getting pretty big
adoption there as well,
especially from the from the dev
aspect to it, then we'll move
into continuous deployment from
the ops perspective, we'll
probably touch on some of the
paradigms that we talked about
before, like get ops and open
policy agent, but more high
level and where that fits in.
And then of course, you can't,
can't talk about ci CD right now
without talking about dev sec
ops and adding the security
aspect to it there. What we're
seeing in terms of adoption, and
what kind of practices and
policies are easy to implement
in ci, CD, which ones are harder
and where some of the pitfalls
are. And then we're going to
build our own pipeline
throughout this. And we're each
going to pick your own tools and
talk about what we liked and
didn't like, and, and we'll,
we'll show that off. And I dare
say, Well, I guess it's we're
open source, we get to put it
out there. But we'll have to
document our code this time, I
guess, well, we'll do it just
just for this one time, we'll
document that code. And we'll
put that up there. That's our
plan. If you'd like to see
something different. You know,
we're feedbacks always important
to us. So feel free to reach
out. Thanks a lot, everybody.
Appreciate it. And
Jamie Duncan: thanks for joining
us again.
John Osborne: Thanks, everyone.
Stay safe, Happy Thanksgiving.