Jamie Duncan: All right, and
thanks for joining us on the
first episode of 2021. For the K
files, this is Episode 12.
We had planned to do an episode
in late November, early December
to round out 2020. And then the
world kind of ended.
And then the world never really
started back up. So we will get
back to the CI CD series we
talked about, we just honestly
do not have the bandwidth in our
brains to do that extra work and
to be able to deliver any kind
of meaningful thought on it. So
what we talked about earlier,
and we were kind of figuring
out, we knew we wanted to record
something we knew we wanted to
get something out there. And the
first thing I think it was out
of I think, john, you're the one
that said it maybe it was you,
Tarik, I don't remember which,
but why is why is it all so damn
hard? Like, and that's what
we're gonna kind of try to
explore. And it may take a
couple of different directions.
I think, john, you're thinking
like, why is it so hard to get
started in it? That's kind of
where your brain is. My brain is
more? Why is it so hard to solve
a problem in our industry right
now? Why does everything take
400 extra things when it didn't
feel like it used to do that?
torque?
Tariq Islam: Yeah, I love the
same mind to do Jamie, I am at a
point now where it's like, I
can't even Hello World Without
googling eight things. And
there's just no getting away
from that now, every time I
think john, you put it best,
every time you sit down at your
computer, it's like you have to,
you're starting a whole project
from scratch, and it's gonna
take you eight years to,
John Osborne: to get anywhere.
It is I mean, it's the, I think
that trend has been, you know,
where thing is getting harder
and maybe optimizing for, you
know, really use cases that
aren't in the now has been
happening for a while. But then
with 2020, for me, personally,
you know, I was just kind of
like, wiped out emotionally all
year. And the time I had to work
was in was just not as much that
as the year before. And so, you
know, sometimes, you know, I'd
be doing meetings and other
stuff, and you know, non coding
and non, you know, real hands on
keyboard stuff. And then, you
know, I'd sit down after like
two or three weeks, I'm not
doing anything. And, you know, I
have a lot of experience, but it
was like starting over. You know
what I mean? Because it's like,
none of that stuff's in short
term memory, it would take so
long to get back to where you
were. And it, I spent a lot of
time just thinking about, you
know, I think some of us were,
we're lucky that we had a
fundamental baseline knowledge
of things. And we saw things
like, you know, Kubernetes, and
serverless, and all these types
of things that are in the know
now, but I think if you're
starting now, it's, it's
actually really hard because you
don't have, you know, deep
learning experience or
understands, like, deep
networking, or how, like, the
software defined network just
kind of makes sense to you and
those types of things. And so,
you know, it's like, where
people ask me, like, how should
I get started, and I try not to
be too prescriptive, because
everyone learns differently.
But, you know, I do have some,
some thoughts on it still,
Tariq Islam: I'm gonna, I'm
gonna call out also parents,
right? I mean, during COVID, we
got we got knocked around really
hard, all year long, and we
still kind of are, and the
exhaustion between the
navigating the pandemic, and
work, and the kids. And just
things happening, you know, by
the time you sit down, and
you're like, you know, what,
today's the day that I'm finally
going to learn go, right, right,
right. And it just, it just, you
just don't have the energy for
it. And then you get that
anxiety and then you run out of
time, because you know, you got
a kid screaming, or you can,
something else has come up,
that's higher priority than
learning a language that you
probably won't end up using on a
regular basis tomorrow.
John Osborne: I mean, I had so
much anxiety, like we're also
building this house way over
budget, like, you know,
financial stuff, and like, I had
so much anxiety for a lot of
2020 that I would go 90 days
without returning somebody text
messages like people wish me
happy birthday in August. I
replied in like, November,
December, and then I got so much
anxiety because one day I just
like had a cup of coffee and I'm
like a reply though. And then
they started replying right
away, like I replied, You know,
it took me nine days to reply,
they replied right away, and
then
they replied right away. That
was john. And then and then I
just replied to those their text
messages like last week. And so
it's like, if I can't even reply
to a text message from a friend
like how am I supposed to sit?
There do all this stuff, but
it's like, you know, it's just
been crazy.
Jamie Duncan: Yeah, there's got
to be something to that because
I kind of live my life in a in a
state of interrupt.
John Osborne: You really do. I'm
actually floored with how, like
you can context switch so
easily, Jamie, that it's kind
Jamie Duncan: of right. I do it
constantly, right. So it's
purely a learning Skill because
I have no attention span
whatsoever. And I used to think
I had this amazing ability to
focus. And when I got a little
self awareness, I realized I
wasn't focusing at all. I was
just spinning 50 plates at once.
Yeah. And so I always thought
that kind of burnout. I wasn't
burnout proof, no one's burnout
proof, but I thought I was more
resistant to it than other
people. And I felt it. And I
think that, and I've kind of
built in my own head, the thing
that I value my own skill, is it
if if it's just if the thing
between me and doing something
well is hard work, I feel okay.
That 100 we're sitting down to
knock it out, I'm good. If I've
got to outwork somebody, I've
got that in the back. Man the
past few months, like more times
than I want to admit freely, I
would be sitting at my desk and
realize I was staring at the
same screen for 10 minutes. And
then the only thought in my head
was go lay on the couch in the
other room.
John Osborne: Oh, yeah. I mean,
like, we're just
Jamie Duncan: like the work like
it's oppressive. And I don't
know how much of that is just
sort of, I don't I don't know
how much of the Why is
everything so damn hard, is
because the world we're living
in is essentially a wood
chipper.
John Osborne: I think it's
they're related. I mean,
everything has been getting
harder. But the emotional energy
that you have to do it all.
Again, we're just not there. I
mean, there were times Yeah,
we're not like, you know, I have
to be on video a lot, too. So
and I'm introverted. So you
know, two hours being on video
talking a lot. Like, yeah, I'd
have to lay down after the
middle, you know, like,
Jamie Duncan: lay down, you mean
fetal position. And
John Osborne: then I'm gonna go,
you know, cry in the shower
floor.
Jamie Duncan: I was actually so
I had lunch with a friend, a
good friend of mine, like, we
worked together for years. And
so we're sitting, you know,
we're doing the whole social
distancing. But we hadn't seen
each other in months. And we
were kind of in she was in the
bubble. pretty consistently. So
like, we're like, we've shared
enough germs that we're kind of
in the same in the same bubble.
And we hadn't seen her since God
before Thanksgiving. So we had
lunch yesterday. And she's like,
How are y'all doing? Like, how's
the family and the only thing I
could express to her was, I
don't have any capacity left.
Like, I'm just empty. And but
the list of things on my to do
list is not empty. It's not
going down. And part of it is
that the industry has gotten so
nuts and I don't know another
word to put to it. Yeah. But it
was like, it's,
Tariq Islam: there's this. I
think I might have a term for
it. It's
it. There's, it's like a
fetishization of abstraction. I
feel like, I'm going to put it I
maybe that's not the right term,
but I feel like that's the right
term. It's just everything. And
I think that's why I end up
having to, like, if I want to do
hello world, you know, 15 years
ago, 10 years ago, take you like
45 seconds, right? Sit down, do
it knock it out. Now. It's like
frameworks on frameworks on
abstractions, and just doesn't,
I'm in the trap. Yeah, exactly.
Like someone that personality
has been around for a long time,
though. Cuz I remember, the
first time I actually got my
first job out of college, I just
wrote c++ and didn't talk to
anyone, which I, which I didn't
like, at the time, but now I'd
be like, Oh, that's amazing job
dream job, like.
John Osborne: But the first time
I actually looked at somebody
else's code, as part as a full
time coder, was like, there's it
was Java code. And there was
like, eight levels of
abstraction and like clicking
this abstract classes interface,
and you got to actually see what
the find like three lines of
code. And I do feel like there's
a personality in tech that just
likes that, like, it's a very,
quote unquote, clean to them.
Tariq Islam: If that makes
sense, that that abstraction,
that abstraction, you know, when
you I mean, that, that that
object oriented, Java
abstraction, right, the the
interfaces and the
implementations and the
templating. And all that. That's
when that's when I feel like, at
least for me, I was like this,
someone's gonna over engineer
the hell out of something using
this. And lo and behold, you
know, now we're here and
everything feels over
engineered. Everything's got to
be an abstracted framework.
Everything's got to be, you
know, some sort of standard. So
I feel for folks that are
entering into the industry. I
mean, I see folks on Twitter
that are, you know, starting
their journey in tech as a
developer. You see, Jamie
mentioned 100 days of code.
It's, it feels I feel exhausted
for them.
Jamie Duncan: Yeah, now that's
legit. So I mean, I'm doing a
writing project.
John Osborne: Great, john, every
aspects gotten harder. I mean,
if you look at front end
developers Even or something
like that, where it's like
before, you could just write
some JavaScript and, you know,
now it's like, it just feels so
much more, more complicated.
Even doing web development, you
know, this, in front end
development can get super
complicated. Especially if you
start doing things like some of
the advanced html5 elements and
things like that, I actually
think it can get more
complicated than the back end
development, because there's
like, the artistic side to it.
Tariq Islam: Part of it is also,
you know, I guess back in the
day, I don't want I hate saying
that, because it makes me feel a
little old. But back in the day,
you know, you only had so many
languages and frameworks to
choose from, like, for me, it
was basically c++, Java, jQuery,
CSS, PHP, go right or not go not
actually, like, take those and
run with it, right. And
everything was built off of
that, and it was great. And you
learn all the concepts and
picking up new languages is not
that big of a deal. You know,
but now it's, it's, I feel like
I could I could pick up a
language Yes, but it what's
gonna, is it gonna be relevant
in two weeks?
John Osborne: Before I feel like
languages the difference, what,
like 15 years ago, the
difference in languages was
largely syntax. And now it's
different fundamental ways of
thinking, if you think about
functional programming, versus
like rust versus go and there's
a lot of, it's more than it's a
lot more than syntax. Now, you
actually have to retrain your
brain. In some cases, languages
went from being general purpose
to specialized in a way, but but
there's but people still try to
use them from purpose languages.
Oh, yeah.
Tariq Islam: Use go for
everything.
Jamie Duncan: One of the things,
of course, duh. I mean, this is
a Kubernetes. podcast, that has
to be the answer. So there, I'm
working on a little writing
project for for a thing. And
part of like, the little
introduction chapter, or
paragraph is a little bit of a
history lesson. And I was
looking up some dates earlier
today. And it really kind of
blew me away because I'm
thinking about them in the
context of this. We're on this
runaway train. Things are
getting harder, exponentially.
And when did that start? And I
don't know when it certainly
didn't start with Kubernetes.
But it certainly didn't start
with Docker. It didn't start
with whatever. But just to kind
of put it in context. openshift
to Dotto, so we all we were all
at Red Hat at the time.
openshift to Dotto was December
2013. So that was just over
seven years ago. And that feels
like at least 47 years ago. It
really does.
John Osborne: I mean, I can show
you a picture of me for 2013 20
years.
Tariq Islam: I mean, to be fair,
though, to be fair, the last
year feels like it was 40 years
ago.
Jamie Duncan: I know it but I
get that. I thought that but
then I was like So look, I had
to look up some other dates.
Kubernetes one Dotto was only a
year and a half after that.
Yeah, there was only 18 months
John Osborne: before filling
every year, yeah, celery gets
Jamie Duncan: gray and gray. So
we've been on this train for a
long time, and then it ran into
2020. And we all fit in a wood
chipper is the only thing the
only analogy I can draw.
John Osborne: You know, part of
the issue is the the technology
is iterating. So much faster
than where most organizations
are now, that every year that
gap gets greater and greater.
And so every year, it just feels
like I mean, if you look at the
technologies that you know, what
is supposed to be like the
simplest way to get up and
running, you might think that
might be you know, a managed
serverless instance, right? But
then you go look at it, and it's
like, Okay, well, I need more
than just the serverless
framework, you know, I gotta
connect it to an API gateway.
And then I gotta get a web
application firewall, and then I
got to learn how the, you know,
kinesis is gonna work. And then
you need a cache and an object
store before you know what
you've learned via service
meshes. Yeah. Before you know
what you've learned, 10
different. Your API gateway.
Yeah, get out, you know, to get
like a web app going. And never
mind the fact that you got to,
you know, learn all this stuff.
You have that.
Tariq Islam: So, so I think I
think there's two there's two
things to this. So when when I
first went when I guess all of
us right when we first learned
Kubernetes It was like, what's a
pod was a service was a
deployment, right? Then there
was the openshift specific stuff
back then anyway, right, the
build config and you know, image
stream and things like that.
That was like 80% of it. Now,
five and a half years later, I
mean, it's a it's a freaking me.
Yeah, I mean, in fact, in fact,
there are folks there are folks
out there learning You know,
Kubernetes at layers of
abstraction, where they're not
even considering things like
learning what an actual
Kubernetes service is, or does
or what the different types of
services there might be, they're
just clicking buttons and
learning Kubernetes, you know,
at the managed layer, where
Yeah, I've touched Kubernetes
before I've installed and spun
up and used Kubernetes. But if
you'd ask them, what a, a, you
know, what the different types
of a service are in Kubernetes,
they probably wouldn't be able
to tell you. And and I don't,
I'm not saying that that's
wrong, or that these individuals
know less. Because, you know,
they don't have to no more than
that, necessarily. But it's a
huge gap. And I would argue that
you still do need to know that
underlying stuff. But I don't
think that I just don't think
that people have the energy for
that I put together a there are
some, there's some folks that,
you know, we've we've hired, and
they're aspiring to specialize
in the Kubernetes ecosystem. So
I put together this, this
curriculum of sorts, and this is
maybe about a year and a half
ago, year and a half ago. And I
kind of went through, you know,
everything that you need to
know, in the community, or from
a community perspective, right,
the big, you know, major tools
and technologies that you should
be aware of, and that you should
be able to talk to, and then
from a product perspective,
right from from, you know,
Google the vendor. And this
document was like five pages
long. And I'm looking at that,
and I'm like, How did this
happen? And this was 18 months
ago. So I if I had to redo that
Doc, I probably have to be
adding another couple of pages.
It's it's not.
Jamie Duncan: So I wonder. So it
was somewhat one of the people
Clark and I work with rich
Schroeder is one of the project
managers for for Google in the
in Google Cloud. He had a tweet
and I was looking for and I
couldn't find it. But he was
talking about some new thing.
Oh, I think it was about like
the some low code product that
Google is, is is has released.
And my response to it, because
it's a pretty compelling thing
for like, I think the tweet, he
had had some statistics, like,
in 2019, X percent of
applications were low code, no
code, and that number is going
up into the right, and all that
kind of thing. And my response
to him was that we abstract away
the things that don't provide
business value. And my thought
at the time was, eventually
virtual machines stopped
providing business value, and we
abstracted them. And we've tried
that a couple of different ways.
And then containers are stopped
are not really the business
value, like getting to the
container, the cost savings of
running Kubernetes running
containerized apps, isn't there
anymore, because it's everyone's
doing it, so no one's doing it
better. So we're abstracting The
next thing? Is that kind of
where is that where your head
is? Tarik? Is that what you're
thinking? Or? Because in to me
that that kind of makes it a
little valid? Because I'm trying
to think, is this good or bad?
Are we building a house of
cards? Or is just the Tower of
Babel getting taller?
Tariq Islam: I think it's the
latter. But at the same time,
it's still technology, right To
this day, you know, however many
years we've we've had Linux,
right? It's always the network.
It's always DNS, it always comes
back to the fundamentals. And I
think the risk is that, with
this sprawl that we're
experiencing, and the sheer
velocity and the acceleration of
of this tech proliferation, I
guess we can call it, it's gonna
get harder and harder for folks
to not just keep up. But even to
start, right. And I think what's
going to have to happen is folks
are going to have to start from
an abstracted level, and then
work their way down on a case by
case basis, which is not ideal.
But
John Osborne: if someone asks
you how to get started, what do
you normally kind of advice that
you give them? Because for me,
personally, the way I learned is
to build apps, or to build
things that, like I want to
build and kind of learn by
doing, but I can't, like I can't
just sit down and read, if I
have all the fundamental
framework. Yeah, I can read the
docs and things will click but
like, if I'm starting up from
scratch, like I don't even read
the docs until after I start
using it because nothing will
click.
Tariq Islam: So interestingly
enough, I'm actually I'm
actually doing this with a with
a couple of folks. Again, these
are the same individuals that
that are brand new to the space.
So it's really interesting to
see how they're taking all of
this up. And it's gonna take at
least a year to two for them to
get caught up. But I actually
had them start with getting a
solid understanding of what
makes up a container. Like I had
them start at that level. Right?
And I told them, don't touch
Kubernetes. Don't touch any of
the products right at the vendor
level. Don't even think about
that stuff. Just get good with
containers. Linux and Linux
networking like it, you know,
get those fundamentals down,
because as soon as you do that
everything else just gets easier
from there, it just flows right?
It'll take longer. But once you
have that foundation, and I
think that's what's so critical
about this, right, I feel like
folks are starting at a at an at
an abstracted level, that's not
giving them a proper foundation.
For example, if I'm, if I'm
billing myself as a Kubernetes,
expert, and I've only ever
touched, you know, Eks, and aka
s, and G, ke, and all these, you
know, automated offerings, I
might be good at all of these
automated offerings. But as soon
as I'm asked about, you know,
something lower than that, I get
hung up. So that's, I think, you
know, it's, it's, it's a point
of exposure that I think folks
are, it's the blind spot,
actually,
Jamie Duncan: I guess that's
what put it, at least in my
personal experience, I've always
found it easier to go up the
stack as opposed to down the
stack. Are we? Do you all agree
with that, or the percentage so
like, we're gonna have a whole
lot of people that have to go
down the stack, we're gonna have
to figure out how to account for
that. Being, you know, the
older, current, get off my lawn
generation, in our industry.
Tariq Islam: Yeah, I don't I
don't mean to gatekeepers here.
That's not I hope that's not the
tone that we're taking, you
John Osborne: know, trying to be
the opposite. It's like, how do
we make it more?
Jamie Duncan: How do we make how
do we make that consumable?
consumable? Yeah.
Tariq Islam: I think the culture
has to change, right? Like, I
think I think we have to
promote, we have to start as a
tech industry, tech Twitter,
right, like social media, I
think we have to start promoting
the this notion that it's okay
to start from the bottom and to
go slow, right there. This is
not a race. And, and having a
good foundation from the basics.
And the fundamentals is only
going to make everything else
that much easier, you'll
accelerate and your velocity
will get to a point where it
matches everybody else's. Right.
But you got to spend the time
and get get get those
fundamentals down. And I think
we have to promote that type of
thing and reward it.
Jamie Duncan: I don't know. I
don't, I don't know that I'm
100% there. And the reason Are
those the reason that I'm not
sure there is are those 100 100
days of code people there is
there is in this massive influx
of people making 725 an hour who
are going through some Bootcamp,
they saved up for self driving
through some program, like 100
days of code. And they're
looking at 6070 $80,000 a year
Junior, whatever jobs, I don't
want to slow them down. I don't
want to tell them to take it
slow, because $7 an hour sucks.
John Osborne: That's a whole
there's a whole slew of people
out there, which I found myself
on this kind of subgroup of
Twitter, where and I think it's
awesome, by the way, but they
they basically use
certifications to you know, pump
up their salary. I would and I
think that's awesome, by the
way. And I do think we did the
certifications episode. You
know, I do think it does provide
a good baseline knowledge. But
yeah, they're out there. And,
you know, they're getting all
these certifications, and
they're getting really high paid
jobs, and which is awesome. But
then how do we take every little
practical experience? Yeah,
Jamie Duncan: I found that
experience. And the other
thought that popped into my head
was, and it stuck in my head. I
mean, this is I guess, a year or
so ago, was talking Duffy
Cooley, who is Oji Kubernetes.
awesome guy. I worked with him
at VMware. I think he's he's
moved on to a different role.
Now. He's, yeah. He was talking
about how we're we being the
Royal we in industry, in it are
massively outnumbered. And he
had some numbers. And I wish I
remembered the numbers. But my
brain doesn't do that. Talking
about like, the number of
applications, the number of
servers, the number of thing
widgets in it over the next five
years, and how we would, at the
current rate of growth of the it
workforce, we'd all be
responsible personally, for like
50,000 servers. We're gonna be
drastically outnumbered for what
the world is doing and the world
the fact that the world is
becoming this IoT platform.
Yeah. So we have to get these
people in, we have to figure out
how to get them up to speed. And
I think maybe part of it is that
maybe we make specialization a
little bit more. Okay.
John Osborne: I think it has to
be because if you look at like
even managed services, right,
like if you use a managed
database, that doesn't, that
helps you have less people on
your team that need to know,
deep database level knowledge,
but still to do all the backups,
the synchronization, the what
happens when a production outage
happens, like you still need to
have some people that go really
deep into databases, right?
Inside rant I actually the more
I thought about it, I think this
kind of this sprawl of
technologies actually happen
first at the data layer, not at
the application layer. Because
if you think about how fast we
went from just using SQL
databases to all the different,
no SQL databases, to all the
things with caching and
invalidation to brokers, and
queues, and Kafka, and all that
stuff, and how fast that layer
happened, that actually, to me
happened first, and everyone
knows what CAP theorem is now
and things like that, where it's
like, okay, that's a problem
that we didn't have to that got
a lot harder, a lot faster, just
kind of a specialization of the
data layer. But that did happen
because of scale issues. I think
that part of the challenge is
like, well, not everyone's
having a scale issue, right.
Jamie Duncan: Yeah. So and then
I guess, to top it all off, you
know, not only are all of those
things happening, they're
happening in an ever increasing
rate. And at least in the US,
but we're certainly not the only
group suffering from this.
Society is, you know, in a
horrible state right now, in a
lot of places. Like, like, I'm
just sort of, I don't want to be
a Debbie Downer, but man, kind
of a crap way to be right now.
John Osborne: It is because they
don't have the emotional energy.
I mean, it's like somebody who's
got shot in the street, and I'm
supposed to sit down. And you
know what I mean? Like, yeah,
deep. And I was like, I can't
I'm sorry, I just can't do it.
Yeah,
Tariq Islam: well, I was I was
having a very productive day on
January 6, up until the coup,
and right at that point, that's
when I realized what was
actually happening. I just kind
of stopped working. And it
wasn't even like a conscious
decision, right? Where I was
like, Okay, I'm going to cancel
all meetings, and I'm not going
to do anything at work, I'm
taking the rest of the day off,
it was literally like, it's
like, my, my brain just stopped.
Right. And I just, I was combing
through social media, looking
for whatever coverage I could
find, and looking at the
pictures and the videos and the
the sheer pandemonium of it all.
I was just in desperate state of
disbelief. And I couldn't, I
completely forgot about work.
And I was like, mid, like, in
the middle of typing an email
when when this all went down.
And I, you know, I got to a
point Finally, where, you know,
I told I told folks, you know,
please, please do what you got
to do for, for your safety and
for your mental health. But, uh,
man, there was a couple of
hours, there was just a total
total pause. There was somebody
John Osborne: in that there was
somebody at the Capitol yelling
Turn on the gas. I mean, how am
I supposed to work? during that?
How am I supposed to work?
People getting shot? How am I
supposed to work when there's
people on Reddit even
bankrupting a $10 billion hedge
fund? Right? It's been really
hard. It's like, it's,
Tariq Islam: we'll see that
thing, things, things. I mean,
this is a really good mirror of
what's been happening in tech.
Not that tech, is that tragic,
but what I'm saying is that
there's so many things
happening, you know, our memory
is only so long. And January 6,
feels like half of an eternity
ago. And we don't even we're not
even, we're barely talking about
it. Now. Right now, we're
talking about GameStop. And, you
know, market manipulation by
retail investors, and is that
even mid relation, and they're
sticking it to the man, you
know, the hedge fund managers
and things like that.
Jamie Duncan: But also
weaponizing, Wall Street.
Tariq Islam: Right? Right. And
three weeks ago, we literally
had a coup of our government.
John Osborne: So we have no
emotional energy, we sit down,
and technology's a billion times
harder than it was five years.
Yeah,
Tariq Islam: I think I think the
theme that we're all getting at
here is, I think we just need to
just, I think we need to slow
things down just a bit for
ourselves. You know, I don't
think we can slow down the pace
of everything outside of us. But
I think we have to, I think we
have to make it make it okay, to
go a little bit slower. And
actually, Jamie, I like that,
you fact that the fact that you
brought up the fact that you
brought up about individuals
that you know, are getting into
this space, and don't have that
luxury of time, right, I feel
like you know, a lot of what
I've said is from a place of
privilege. And for folks that
have that sense of financial
urgency, absolutely, you know,
do what you have to do. And when
you get there and you will
absolutely get there. I still
think it's important that you do
take some time once you're in
the door to go back and and get
down to those fundamentals.
Right. I think everyone owes it
to owes it to themselves to do
that at some point, maybe not at
the very beginning. But at some
point.
John Osborne: I think it's a
really good point about you
know, it's okay to go slow
because everyone's got Slower
right now. And if somebody calls
you and expects you to go the
same speed, which that's
happened to me a couple times in
past year, it's like, I feel
like those people are just bots,
honestly. It's like, it's like,
do you realize what's going on?
You know, have some, you know,
show some emotion. Talk, I
Jamie Duncan: love the idea of
telling people to slow down and
catch their breath and do what
they need to do to be okay. How?
Like, none of this other stuff.
None of these other buzz saws
that are flying in our head are
slowing down
Tariq Islam: in the back to back
meetings every day, certainly
aren't helping, because now we
don't have to, you know, travel
to a meeting or even change
meeting rooms. Right? It's
literally just clicking a button
to end one call. And then five
and a half seconds later joining
the next one.
John Osborne: I've been like,
it's okay for me not to answer
the call. Like, just because I'm
not another call doesn't mean
I'm going to answer everybody
that just calls me out of the
blue, or I'm not going to text
back people every right away and
all that stuff, because, or else
I just sit here and just do
notifications on my phone for
all day, which I totally could
do, because that's just how
things go right now.
Jamie Duncan: I aspire to say no
more often.
John Osborne: But how to play
more the long game? No.
Jamie Duncan: Yeah, so so we
have to figure out how to slow
down I our industry is moving at
a pace that is approaching, you
know, approaching the speed of
light. The world is falling is
ripping apart at the seams. We
all need to catch our breath.
And I think I don't think
there's like I know that sounds
simplistic, but I don't think
there's anything else we can do.
Tariq Islam: Yeah, I would say
we're about at the halfway point
as as depressing as that might
sound right in this whole
pandemic. And with everything
else going on, we're still we
still get, I would say at least
by maybe, maybe the summer.
We'll we'll start to see normal
again. And we can start catching
up on things.
Jamie Duncan: Yeah, I hope to be
able to visit my friends in
September.
John Osborne: I hadn't even
thought test today.
But yeah,
Jamie Duncan: yeah, it's just
and I wish we had some sort of
piffy thing. I wish that we
could do some headspace
meditation. Yeah, no, I'm
Tariq Islam: not about that. It
is it a lot of that stuff that
we've been doing over the last
year has felt a little forced.
You know, you kind of do it
because everyone else is doing
it. But sometimes you just want
to throw your hands up.
John Osborne: Were there
anything, anything you guys did
over the pandemic to help you
clear your head,
Jamie Duncan: I've tried 1000
things none of them have stuck.
Tariq Islam: I started working I
started exercising outside,
especially after a cold, which
sounds kind of crazy. But it's
been a pretty nice release. For
me, at least it's you know, a
bit of a shock to the system to
go outside when it's, you know,
2530 degrees and and be
physically active. But that
that's it's been refreshing,
right? And it works for me. But
it's not for everybody.
Jamie Duncan: The thing that
that I've kind of realized and I
told this to my wife and she
looked at me like Oh, you're
just now figuring this out the
another line from a movie in
frozen too. And we all have kids
I know that you too have watched
frozen to 1000 times but there's
no doubt in my mind completing
the fifth on that. arc if you
haven't watched frozen two you
have to tomorrow. Olaf the
snowman like crazy stuff is
happening in the front of the
movie. And all these little kids
are sticking icicles in Olaf.
And they're making him look
funny and it's just a laugh line
and they asked him if he's okay
and he looks around he's like
you know, we're controlling when
things are out of control we do
what we can to do something and
control I don't remember the
exact line but I like Tarik is
going outside and working out
like rocky in the I've gone like
I'm trying to turn my my
backyard workshop into like the
new Yankee workshop. Like so
I've got like I'm doing all
these ridiculous projects that
are way over my head and ability
or scope. Grab what you can, I
guess is the only thought that I
have. Grab onto something that
gives you a little bit of a
smile, like tark targets working
out. me making things out of
wood that isn't what you're
maybe slowing down a little bit
by looking at something else and
making that important to you.
Tariq Islam: Yeah, that's that's
actually I think you just keyed
in on something right there
right now it's not so much
distracting but it's it's it's a
shift in focus. Right so you're
not feeling like you're always
just constantly driving towards
you know that that competitive
like I need to know more tech
Then the next person. And and it
gives, it gives you a sense of
control that I think everybody
kind of lost last year when the
pandemic hit. And I think that's
really important. You know, and
that's also I think, why we did
this episode like this, right,
because I think as much as we
would love to regale you with
the intricacies of ci CD
infrastructure, and all the
permutations they're in, I think
it's, and we needed to pause
right, and communicate that it's
okay to do that. And shift focus
a little bit acknowledge the
pains that we've experienced
over the last year. And, and,
you know, be real about, you
know, put a little bit of
humanity in, in, in even a tech
podcast, I
Unknown: guess.
Jamie Duncan: I think that's a
great spot to kind of close it
up on it's john, any closing
thoughts, words of wisdom?
John Osborne: Now, what
Jamie Duncan: do you what do you
do to stay sane, john,
Tariq Islam: he was oddly
started there.
John Osborne: I watched a lot of
the office. There you go. I
started working out a couple
months ago. And during the
pandemic, towards the end, I
started taking walks at night,
which was really helpful,
because I wasn't really having
enough time to work out. And
then at the start of the
pandemic, I was trying to keep
the same speed. So it started, I
was sleeping like three or four
hours a night and just totally
destroyed. My ability to focus
on that stuff. So one thing I
realized is like, you know, if,
if 2020 if there's ever a 2020,
again, hope there isn't, you
know, I'm gonna prioritize
getting a certain amount of rest
from from the start and just try
to live that every day because I
totally just tried to keep the
same pace and just really,
everything kind of fell apart
after about two months of four
hours of sleep. So I think sleep
is just one of those things
where you kind of take it for
granted, but it's, you know,
you're paying it somewhere,
right? You can your neck, if
your body wants eight hours, you
can't just get for continuously
and expect things to be okay,
because they won't
Jamie Duncan: get you're gonna
pay up at some point. Yes. Or
someone is, yeah, maybe your
kids and maybe your wife and
maybe the guy, you know, not
wearing a mask at the gas
station. Exactly. Which may have
happened to me once about a
month ago.
John Osborne: You're putting it
on a credit card, and some you
know, there's interest on that.
So,
Jamie Duncan: all right,
everyone, well, we appreciate
it. Next time, and we're gonna
try one of the things that we
want to control is getting back
on a good schedule in 2021. And
we'll pick up ci CD next time,
and until then, take a deep
breath. The work will be there.
When you after you've calmed
down and enjoyed something
that's right.
Tariq Islam: And mask
Jamie Duncan: up. Yeah, and wear
your damn mask or I'm gonna yell
at you.
John Osborne: Or a cover is
supposed to cover your nose.
Okay. Yeah.
Tariq Islam: My God seriously.
John Osborne: covers you.
Jamie Duncan: Thanks a lot,
everyone.